<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The substance of several sermons, from John, ix. 39 Preach'd at the request of a friend, and now publish'd for the benefit of the publick. By Nathanael Wyles, an unworthy labourer in Christ's vineyard.</title>
            <author>Wyles, Nathaniel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3770B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222177</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833398</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833398</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37874</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37874)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2164:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The substance of several sermons, from John, ix. 39 Preach'd at the request of a friend, and now publish'd for the benefit of the publick. By Nathanael Wyles, an unworthy labourer in Christ's vineyard.</title>
                  <author>Wyles, Nathaniel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>63, [1], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and sold at his house in Shadwel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on D8v.</note>
                  <note>"A funeral sermon" has caption title and separate pagination; register begins with B1.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John IX, 39 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37874:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37874:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SUBSTANCE Of Several SERMONS, FROM JOHN, ix. 39.</p>
            <p>PREACH'D At the Requeſt of a Friend, and now Publiſh'd for the Benefit of the Publick.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nathanael Wyles,</hi> an Unworthy Labourer in Chriſt's Vineyard.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>I am ſmall and deſpiſed, yet do I not forget thy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts,</hi> 
               <bibl>Pſal. 110. 141.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and ſold at his Honſe in <hi>Shadwel,</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:37874:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37874:2"/>
            <head>THE SUBSTANCE OF Several DISCOURSES, From <hi>John</hi> IX, and XXXIX:</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> Jeſus <hi>ſaid, For Judgment I am come into this World; That they which ſee not, might ſee; and that they which ſee, might be made blind.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN this Chapter you have an Account of Chriſt's curing a man on the Sabboth Day, who was blind from his Birth, which wonderful and miraculous Cure is deſcribed three Ways, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> By the Occaſion and Precedent Circumſtances of it, from the <hi>1ſt.</hi> to the <hi>6th.</hi> verſe: In the laſt Verſe of the former Chapter, you read, <hi>That the Jews and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees took up Stones, to ſtone our dear Saviour;</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37874:3"/> 
               <hi>becauſe he ſaid, before</hi> Abraham <hi>was, I am,</hi> Verſe 58. <hi>But Jeſus hid himſelf, and went out of the Temple, going thro' the midſt of' em, and ſo paſſed by;</hi> and ſays the firſt verſe of this <hi>9th.</hi> Chapter, <hi>As Jeſus paſſed by, he ſaw a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſe 1.</note> 
               <hi>Man that was blind from his Birth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where Chriſt paſſed by, the Evangeliſt doth not tell us; but the word imports, a paſſing by ſome way ſide, when he ſaw this poor man, who was born blind: His being blind from his Birth, is particularly named; becauſe ſuch Blindneſs is judged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable as to the Art of Man. The Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples upon this, came to Chriſt, <hi>and asked him; ſaying, Maſter who did ſin, this man, or</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſe 2.</note> 
               <hi>his Pare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts, that he was born blind;</hi> Chriſt gave them this Anſwer, <hi>That neither this Man nor his Parents had ſinned, but that the Works of God ſhould be made manifest in him.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſe 3.</note> You muſt not underſtand our Saviour here, as either aſſerting, that this blind Man, or his Parents had no ſin, and a degree of Sin, that juſtly deſerved ſuch a Puniſhment; for no man (ſince the Fall) was born, or lived without ſin, except Chriſt, who was holy, harmleſs, and without ſin. But the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt's Anſwer is this, <hi>viz.</hi> That this Affliction came not upon this Man, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for any perſonal Sin of his own, (for he could not be guilty of actual ſin, before he was born) nor yet for any ſin that his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents had committed, <hi>But that the Works of</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37874:3"/> 
               <hi>God might be manifeſted, and made glorious in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 11 4.</note> 
               <hi>him;</hi> both his Work of Power, in afflicting of him, and his Works of Mercy, in Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him; as there are Afflictions, which <note place="margin">Note.</note> are Puniſhments from God, for ſin; ſo there are ſome that are only Tryals. <hi>For a ſeaſon (if need be)</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Ye are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſs, thro manifold Temptations, that the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>Tryal of your Faith, being much more precious than of Gold that periſheth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>might be found unto Praiſe and Honour at the appearing of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho' ſin is the Cauſe of all Afflictions; <note place="margin">Note.</note> yet God doth not always afflict his People for ſin: Sometimes he doth it, to try their Faith and Patience, and to make known his Power, and Goodneſs, in helping and ſaving of them: But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> This Cure is deſcribed by the Manner and Means of it, <hi>And that was Clay and Spittle,</hi> a very unlikely Means to effect <note place="margin">Verſe 6 7.</note> ſuch a great Cure. Verſe 6, 7. <hi>Jeſus ſpat upon the Ground, and made Clay of the Spittle, and he anointed the Eyes of the blind Man with the Clay; and ſaid unto him, go waſh in the Pool of</hi> Siloam, <hi>and he went his way therefore, and waſhed, and came away ſeeing.</hi> Obſerve this by the way, That true Faith, joyned <note place="margin">Note.</note> and accompanied with hearty and ſincere Obedience, never faileth the Expectation of them that exerciſeth it: He went to the Pool (believing the means would do,) and came away ſeeing</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:37874:4"/>
            <p>Chriſt wrought this Miracle, to prove his Divinity and Godhead, which the Jews denied; and that he might do it effectually, He <hi>1ſt.</hi> makes choice, not only of a Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but one that was born blind, that was incurable to the Judgment of humane art. <hi>2dly.</hi> He made uſe of ſuch Means (to effect this Cure) that had not any appearance of Vertue in it; nay, the Means he uſed, was more like to put out the Eyes of one that ſaw, than give ſight to one that was blind. This ſhews the Power and God-head of Chriſt, who is able not only to work with <note place="margin">Note.</note> little Means or without Means, but to effect great and ſtrange things, even by contrary Means, as here.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly.</hi> By the Conſequents, or Events that enſued upon it which are theſe Four, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>1st.</hi> The man cur'd (being returned home to his Parents,) <hi>The Neighbours brought him to the Phariſees, informing them what a Cure Chriſt had done, and wrought,</hi> from the <hi>8th.</hi> to <hi>14th</hi> ver. This Cure was ſo mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, <hi>That the Neighbours when they ſaw the Man, they were at a ſtand, whether it was he, or not; ſome ſaid, it was he, others ſaid it was</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>not he; but he ſaid, I am he that was blind. Then they asked him, how his eyes were opened, and who opened them? and he ſaid, a man that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 10. 11.</note> 
               <hi>is called Jeſus, made clay, and opened mine eyes.</hi> He told them not only, who did this Cure, but the Means by which it was effected. But</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37874:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> He being brought to the Phariſees, (whether in the Temple, or in ſome great Court, is not certain, nor material.) <hi>They enquired of him, how Chriſt cured him, and where he was? which at the preſent he could not tell: They chid him ſeverely, for his confeſſing Chriſt, and caſt him out upon that account;</hi> From the <hi>14th.</hi> to <hi>35th, The Phariſees ſeeing the Man, and the Cure, were in a debate among themſelves, whether Chriſt was from</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 15. 16.</note> 
               <hi>God, or not: Some of them ſaid, He was; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſaid he was not, but he was a Sinner, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he kept not the Sabaoth Day;) being in this debate, they asked the blind Man, what he thought of the Man that had opened his eyes?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver 17.</note> 
               <hi>and he ſaid, he is a Prophet: Then they call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Parents, and asked them, if this were their Son, that was born blind, and who cured him, and how he was cured?</hi> to which his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents <note place="margin">Ver. 19, 20, 21.</note> anſwer'd diſcreetly &amp; warily; they ſaid, <hi>That he was their Son, &amp; that he was born blind; but how, or by what means he was cured, they ſaid, they could not tell; he is of Age (ſaid they) ask him, he ſhall ſpeak for himſelf; his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>Parents ſpake theſe Words, becauſe they fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Jews; for the Jews had agreed alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that if any Man did confeſs he was the Chriſt, he ſhould be put out of the Synagogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerve, That Fear is often a tempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Note.</note> to Men, to deny the Truth, or at leaſt not to own it: <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>That the fear of Man, bringeth a Sword:</hi> The <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:37874:5"/> not being able to get any thing out of his Parents, calls for the Man that was blind, and ſaid unto him, <hi>give God the Praiſe, for me know that this Man is a Sinner:</hi> Thus <note place="margin">Ver. 24.</note> far they ſpake well; for the Man had great Cauſe to praiſe God, by whoſe Power exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt his Son, he had received his ſight: But the Deſign of theſe Wretches was to vilifie Chriſt, in, thro', and by whom God the Father is glorify'd: They told the poor Man that Chriſt had cured, that he which had opened his Eyes, was a ſinner; here they maliciouſly defamed Chriſt, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that he was not only a Sinner, but a notorious ſcandalous Sinner: Well, ſays the poor Man, <hi>whether he be a ſinner, or no,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 25.</note> 
               <hi>I know not; but this I know, that whereas I was blind, now I ſee:</hi> They could not by all their Skill, cauſe the Man to deny the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle wrought; he ſtood ſtoutly to affirm that he was born blind, and that Chriſt (whom they ſaid was a Sinner) had cured him: Upon this, they reviled him, and ſaid, <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u art one of his Diſciples, but we are Moſes's</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 27. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Diſciples:</hi> Here they oppoſe <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Moſes;</hi> whereas <hi>Moſes</hi> was but the Type, Chriſt the Antype; they ſpoke honourably of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but revilingly of Chriſt, who was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove him, calling him Fellow, and ſaid, <hi>they knew not whence he was:</hi> They might have <note place="margin">Ver. 29.</note> known, that he was from God; for he did thoſe things, which never Man did, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37874:5"/> could not be effected by any thing leſs than by a divine Power; but their Eyes were blinded, and their Hearts judiciouſly hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as a juſt Judgement, for their wilful ſhutting their Eyes, and rejecting of Chriſt the Son of God: They ſtudied all they could to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hut out the Light, by which they ſhould have ſeen and known from whence Chriſt was: The poor Man marvelled at their Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and blindneſs, in not knowing <hi>from whence</hi> Chriſt was, ſince he had done <note place="margin">Ver. 30.</note> ſuch a great thing, as to open the Eyes of one that was <hi>born blind:</hi> He goes on to prove <note place="margin">Ver. 31.</note> that Chriſt came from Heaven, and was ſent of God. As yet this poor Man did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, <note place="margin">Note.</note> that Chriſt had opened his eyes by an immediate divine Power, but that he was a Prophet ſent of God, who by his Power and Authority, had opened his eyes, <hi>if this Man were not of God;</hi> that is, if he had not <note place="margin">Ver. 32, 33.</note> ſome ſpecial Power and Authority from God, and ſome ſpecial Preſence of God with him, he could do nothing; that is, nothing of this Nature, to open the eyes of one <hi>born blind;</hi> this is a work (as if he had ſaid) that is beyond the Power of Man, and beyond that Power that we read, God did ever betruſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Man with, therefore he muſt be from God; upon this they excommunicated him, <hi>caſting him out</hi> of Communion with the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh <note place="margin">Ver. 34.</note> Church: But,</p>
            <p>3 <hi>ldy.</hi> Chriſt, upon this their dealing thus
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37874:6"/> with the Man, Meets him, and Reveals himſelf more fully to him, from the 35<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> to 39. <hi>Jeſus heard, that they had caſt Him out; and when he had found Him (whether caſually, or</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 35.</note> 
               <hi>by diligent ſearching for Him, is not ſaid.)</hi> He ſaid unto him, doſt thou Believe on the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God?</hi> art thou ready truely to Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Me the <hi>Saviour</hi> of Loſt Sinners? <hi>who am not onely the Son of Man, but the Son of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 36.</note> 
               <hi>God.</hi> The poor man (as yet being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of <hi>Chriſts</hi> God head) <hi>ſaid, who is he, Lord, that I may Believe on him?</hi> As if he had ſaid, <hi>Lord, I am ready to Believe on him, and give up my ſelf in Obedience to him,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 37.</note> 
               <hi>may I but know who he is. Jeſus ſaid unto him, thou haſt both ſeen him, and it is he that talketh with thee.</hi> As if <hi>Chriſt</hi> had ſaid, <hi>I am here, thou haſt not onely ſeen him with the Eyes of thy Body, but thou haſt had Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of his Divine Power, in opening thine Eyes who wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Blind.</hi> Miracles do not work faith, but Confirm it: This poor blind man, had experienc'd a Miracle wrought upon himſelf; but yet he was unbelieving, till <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave him the Revelation of his Word, and ſo reveal'd himſelf more fully to him: Upon this, the man's Faith was Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated, and Confirm'd in <hi>Chriſt; he ſaid, Lord I believe.</hi> Now is the work of faith wrought with Power in his heart: He ſaid, <hi>Lord,</hi> I acknowledge, and receive thee as the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> I am fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37874:6"/> thou art more than a meer man, I do give up my ſelf to thee to be rul'd, and govern'd by thee as my <hi>Lord:</hi> And ſays the Text, <hi>he Worſhiped him:</hi> He fell down <note place="margin">Ver. 38.</note> upon his face before him; and as a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of his Faith in Him as the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> he perform'd ſome exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Act of Adoration to Him.</p>
            <p>But laſtly, <hi>Chriſt</hi> upbraids the <hi>Jews,</hi> for their blindneſs, and unbelief; from the 39, to the end. The Phariſees being with Chriſt <note place="margin">Ver. 39.</note> (when he ſaid) <hi>For Judgment I am come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this World, that they which ſee not, might</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 40.</note> 
               <hi>ſee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Said unto him, Are we blind alſo?</hi> They began to be angry, being proud, and not patient to be thought, or called blind: They look'd upon themſelves as the Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Lights in the <hi>Jewiſh Church:</hi> Now, (ſays <hi>Chriſt)</hi> in anſwer to the Inquiry, <hi>Are we blind alſo? If you were blind, you ſhould have no ſin;</hi> that is, if your Ignorance of me, or of my Goſpel, where ſimple, and not affected, which is the worſt of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, you ſhould not have ſo much ſin, as you have upon you; <hi>but now ye ſay, we ſee your ſin remaineth:</hi> Since you are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinionated, <note place="margin">Ver. 41. Note.</note> that you ſee, and boaſt of your Knowledge in the Law, as if you were the only Perſons that ſaw, or knew any thing, and upon this Preſumption Reject me, and the Doctrine of Salvation, <hi>your ſin remaineth,</hi> and is not pardon'd to you.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:37874:7"/>
            <p>Whence obſerve, that without a true ſaving ſight of ſin, which carrys the Soul <note place="margin">Note.</note> out of its ſelf to Chriſt for Pardon, and Remedy, There is no hope of Pardon, from all the Mercy that is in <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have brought you to the words of my Text, which are big with Mercy, and Judgement, in which words you have theſe three parts. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the Perſon ſpeaking, and that is <note place="margin">The parts of the Text.</note> 
               <hi>Jeſus Chriſt. And Jeſus ſaid:</hi> Theſe words dropt out of the Sweet Mouth and Lips of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who <hi>Taught not as the Scribes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. 7. ult. 29.</note> 
               <hi>but as one having Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> The perſons ſpoken to, namely the <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> a Wiſe and Learned <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 19, 20. 21.</note> People in the Law; they boaſted of their Wiſdom, and Goodneſs, when indeed they were Blind and Ignorant, and in a miſerable condition. Whence obſerve, that peoples <note place="margin">Note.</note>opinion of themſelves, may be better than their ſtates are: <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us of ſome, that are <hi>pure in their own eyes,</hi> and yet <note place="margin">Pro. 30. 12.</note> were not waſh'd from their filthyneſs: Many think and flatter themſelves that they are <hi>Rich,</hi> and full, <hi>and have need of nothing, and know not that they are Poor,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>and Blind, Naked, Wretched, and Miſerable:</hi> Thus, many deceive themſelves, and put a dreadful cheat upon their precious Souls.</p>
            <p>But <hi>3dly.</hi> you have the predicate, or thing ſpoken of, by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to this People, in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37874:7"/> theſe words: <hi>For Judgmemt I am come into this World, that they which ſee not, might ſee; and that they which ſee, might be made Blind;</hi> a ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and a wakening Word!</p>
            <p>Before I lay down the Propoſition, I muſt a little open the word Judgment in the Text, which will give great Light into it.</p>
            <p>Judgment, is taken many ways in the Holy Scripture: <hi>1ſt.</hi> It is ſometimes taken for the Juſt Statutes, and Holy Commandements of <hi>God,</hi> Pſ. 19. 9. <hi>the Judgments of the Lord</hi> (ſays <note place="margin">Pſ. 19. 9.</note> 
               <hi>David) are Pure, and Righteous altogether: 2dly.</hi> For puniſhments Inflicted upon <hi>Chriſt</hi> by <hi>God,</hi> for our ſins, which we muſt have ſuffer'd in <hi>Hell,</hi> had not he born them for us on Earth: Acts. 8, and 33. <hi>In his Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, his Judgment was taken away, and who can declare his Generation?</hi> By humiliation here, is meant the Grave, and the bands of Death, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſuffer'd, and lay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for our Sins; and by Judgment is meant, the Hand (ſays one) and Counſels of <hi>God,</hi> juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afflicting, and puniſhing his Son, our Surety, for our Sins, and ſakes; but this is not meant in our Text. <hi>3dly.</hi> It is taken ſometimes, for the moderation, or meaſure which <hi>God</hi> keeps in Chaſtizing of his People: <hi>O Lord Correct me,</hi> (ſays the <hi>Prophet) but with Judgment; let it be with meaſure, and moderation, not in thine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 10. 24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anger, leſt thou bring me to nothing.</hi> God hath not ty'd himſelf, not to Afflict his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; he will debate with them, but it ſhall be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37874:8"/> in meaſure he keeps time and meaſure with his in afflicting of them, ſo that they cannot enter into Judgment with <hi>God:</hi> But 4th. for the Wrath, and Vengeance of <hi>God,</hi> which he <note place="margin">Mat. 8. 28.</note> will Execute upon Wicked Men, at the laſt day; <hi>the <hi>Lord,</hi> ſays the <hi>Apoſtle,) will Come</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jude. 5. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>with Ten thouſand of his Saints;</hi> to do what? <hi>To Execute Judgment upon all that are Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> &amp;c. The day of Judgment,</hi> will be a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of an Irrevocable Sentence, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, upon all that ſhall then be found Enemies to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his Pure Goſpel: But laſtly: It is alſo ſometimes taken for the Spirit of Wiſdom, and Juſtice, to know and diſcern what is Right, what is wrong, what is Good, and what is Evil. <hi>Give the King</hi> (ſays the Pfalmiſt) <hi>thy Judgments, and thy Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 72. 1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>to the King's Son;</hi> but neither of theſe ſenſes are meant in the Text.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is then meant by Judgment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. 1ſt.</hi> Some by Judgment here under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Eternal Counſel and Decree of God, as if <hi>Chriſt</hi> had ſaid, I am come into this World, to Execute the Righteous Will, and Counſels of my <hi>Father;</hi> and the Event of it is this, <hi>viz.</hi> that ſome, who ſaw not, ſee; and ſome who ſee, in a ſenſe are made blind: This I conceive, is not prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily meant here; 'tis true, <hi>Chriſt</hi> came into the World, <hi>to do the Will of his Father,</hi> and <note place="margin">John 6. 38. 39.</note> to Execute his Eternal Purpoſes of Grace, in the Salvation of Sinners, by his Death; but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37874:8"/> yet I cannot think, that this is meant prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily by Judgement here; tho' ſome great Men, would have it ſo: But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> Others by Judgement here, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Sentence of Condemnation; as if Chriſt had ſaid, I am come to execute the Judgement of Condemnation; but this is not meant by it, for if you take it in this Senſe, you'll find it hardly reconcileable with what is ſaid; <hi>John 3. 18. God ſent not his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 10. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Son to condemn the World, but that the World thro' him might have life:</hi> Chriſt's firſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming was not as a Judge, but as a Saviour; he came not in the days of his Fleſh, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn Sinners, but by his <hi>Death and bloody</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 19. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Agony.</hi> to ſave them from Hell, and Wrath: I had rather Fall in, and acquieſce with thoſe Divines, that by Judgment here, underſtand the ſpiritual Government of the World by Chriſt, committed to him as Mediator, by Chriſt, committed to him as Mediator, by God his Father, and managed by him with perfect Equity and Righteouſneſs: Thus Judgement is ſometimes taken in Scripture; <hi>The Father</hi> (ſays Chriſt,) <hi>judgeth no man,</hi> that is, <hi>but by his Son,</hi> for he has commited all <note place="margin">John 5. 22. 16. 11.</note> Judgements to him, thus it is underſtood in my Text: God governs and judges the World now by his Son Chriſt, that all men may honour him, as they honour the Father, and great part of this Government of the World by Chriſt, was his promulging, and publiſhing his everlaſting Goſpel, which is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37874:9"/> called the word of Life, <hi>the Power of God,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 15. Rom. 1. 16.</note> 
               <hi>to the ſaving of them that believe,</hi> and the Law of Faith: The Effect of this is twofold, <hi>1ſt,</hi> That they which ſee not, might ſee, i. e. that thoſe poor Souls who are ſpiritually blind, and ſo utterly unable to ſee, and find the way that leads to Life, might thro' the Spirit (as this Man born blind ſaw clearly) be enlightned into the ſaving Knowledge of Chriſt, and of the divine Truths of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Effect is, and a dreadful one too, that they w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> See might be made Blind; that is, that thoſe who think they ſee, and boaſt of their Knowledge (as theſe did) might through their prejudice to the Goſpel, &amp; Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, be more Blind, than they were from their Birth: There are two things ſignifi'd, in making perſons blind; firſt, to keep men from ſeeing, and knowing the Truth, when the Light of it is ſet before them; this is a dreadful judgment, and how many are there, in this miſerable caſe, they have the Light of the Word, ſhining in the midſt of them, and yet they diſcern it not: The Bible is a ſealed Book to many, they know nothing ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly, and feelingly, of the truths and myſteries of the Goſpel: <hi>Their eyes are blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 69. 23.</note> (that tho' the Light ſhine,) they cannot behold it; is not the caſe of ſuch Souls dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to whom the Goſpel is hid? yes (ſays <hi>Paul)</hi> if our Goſpel be hid, it is hid to them
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37874:9"/> that <hi>are loſt.</hi> But <hi>2dly.</hi> To make blind, is to increaſe Ignorance, for the great Abuſe of former Knowledge and Light; this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to them, ſpoken of by <hi>Paul, 2 Theſ. 2. 11, 12. For this Cauſe God ſhall ſend them</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrong Deluſions, that they ſhould believe a Lie, that they all might be damned, who believe not the Truth, but have pleaſure in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs:</hi> This is a dreadful Judgement; but what is the Cauſe of it? Verſe <hi>10th</hi> tells you, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they received not the Love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved:</hi> By Truth is meant <note place="margin">Eph. 1. 13. Rom. 1. 18.</note> the ſaving Truth of the Goſpel, which is called the Word of Truth: There is a Truth natural which the Heathens had, and detained in Unrighteouſneſs, which brought Gods Wrath down from Heaven upon them: There is a ſupernatural Truth from divine Revelation: This is here meant, the Abuſe of which Truth highly provokes God to give up men judicially to the Deluſions of Sin and the Devil; and at laſt (as the juſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and Effect of their rejecting the truth, and believing Lies) are damned: Theſe Wretches, that receive not the Love of the truth, are firſt puniſhed with ſpiritual Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and then with eternal ones; they are firſt blinded here judicially, and then as the juſt Reward, (of their rejecting Chriſt, &amp; the truth as it is in Jeſus) they are damn'd. Having divided, and opened the Text, I ſhall lay down this one general Propoſition, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> That God by Chriſt, in juſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37874:10"/> gives over ſuch as are enemies to his Goſpel, to the Deluſions of the Devil, and their own Hearts, to be hardned and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, while others in Mercy are enlightned, and converted by it.</p>
            <p>That Goſpel which makes the way of Salvation by Chriſt, clear and evident to many ſouls who are in darkneſs, and ſit as in the ſhadow of Death; to others (thro' their Ignorance, Prejudice and Malice, and the righteous Judgment of God, for their Perverſeneſs and Infidelity) proves a means to blind and harden their Hearts: That Word and Goſpel, which to ſome <hi>is a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Life unto Life,</hi> to others thro' their Pride and Unbelief, <hi>is a Savour of Death</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>unto Death.</hi> In this ſenſe, theſe words agree with what was propheſied by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah, He ſhall be for a ſanctuary,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 8. 14, 15.</note> (ſpeaking of Chriſt,) <hi>but for a ſtone of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and for a Rock of Offence to both the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of</hi> Iſrael: For <hi>a Gin, and for a Snare to the Inhabitants of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and many among them ſhall ſtumble and fall, and be broken, ſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 2. 34.</note> 
               <hi>and taken:</hi> And with the words of good old <hi>Simeon,</hi> to <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of our Lord, <hi>This Child is ſet</hi> (ſays he) <hi>for the Fall, and Riſing again of many in</hi> Iſrael; <hi>and for a ſign to be ſpoken againſt.</hi> By the Fall and Riſing again, is here meant undoubtedly, the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and Damnation of many. Chriſt will be the occaſion of many Peoples Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, even of all that reject him, and his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37874:10"/> precious Goſpel, and believe not in him: As Chriſt is the Cauſe of many Peoples Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, even of all <hi>that believe, and ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 4. 12.</note> (for there is no other Name, by which men can be ſaved, but by his): So he is the Cauſe of their Damnation, eventually and accedentually, who oppoſe his Goſpel, and believes not in him; <hi>for he that believeth not ſhall be damned:</hi> This is the thing, which <note place="margin">Mark 16. 16.</note> Chriſt tells us of, in my Text, and is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of by <hi>Paul, Behold I lay in</hi> Sion <hi>a ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling ſtone, and rock of Offence, whoſoever belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 33.</note> 
               <hi>on him, ſhall not be aſhamed, nor confounded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the opening of this weighty Point, I ſhall firſt ſhew you what thoſe ſins are, which provoke God and Chriſt to ſuch a-degree, as to blind and harden men by that means, by which others are enlightened and ſoftned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Lay down ſome Concluſions, for the better clearing up this great Truth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſhew you, how this ſtands with the Holineſs and Goodneſs of God, to give Men up to Blindneſs of Mind, and Hardneſs of Heart, <hi>to believe Lies;</hi> that as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2. 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>they may be damned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Then I ſhall ſum up the whole with ſome practical Application.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Lord, God, the Father of the Spirits of all Fleſh, help thy poor ſinful Duſt, (the meaneſt of all employed in thy Vineyard.) Give him thy holy Spirit, and Wiſdom from above to manage this great Point, for thy Glory, &amp; the</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37874:11"/> 
               <hi>good of Souls. O! let him not darken Counſel, by words without Knowledge, but be led into all truth, and cauſe it to ſhine tranſparently, to the Convincing of the erroneous World, the Converſion of ſinners, and the eſt abliſhing thy Children in their moſt holy Faith,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt's ſake, to whom with thy Self, and eternal Spirit of Truth, be Honour and Glory for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall ſhew you what thoſe ſins are, which provoke God to ſuch a high degree, as to give men over to Blindneſs under the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Would you know what thoſe ſins are, that provoke God to blind and harden many by the Word? I'll tell you in general, They are ſins againſt Knowledge and Light.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> Sins againſt the Light of Nature: There are ſuch ſins, which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, that are of a provoking Nature, <hi>and highly diſpleaſing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>unto God:</hi> When they knew God; that is, by the Light of Nature; for the Light of the Word they had not; as for his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and his Statutes, (ſays the Pſalmiſt) <hi>they have not known them;</hi> they glorified him <note place="margin">Pſ. 147. 20.</note> not as God, but became vain in their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and their fooliſh Hearts were darkened: Theſe Heathens had the Light of Nature, which was ſufficient to let' em know that there was a God, and that He was not like a Man, or a Beaſt, or a creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thing, as they fooliſhly imagined; <hi>for</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:37874:11"/> 
               <hi>that which might be known of God, is manifeſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 29. Ver. 20.</note> 
               <hi>in them, for God hath ſhewed it unto them; for the inviſible things of him, from the Creation of the world, are clearly ſeen.</hi> What is ſeen? Even his eternal Power and Godhead: But how is this ſeen and underſtood? Why, by the things that are made: So that they are without Excuſe, <hi>the Heavens declare Gods</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 1, 2. Ver. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Glory, and the Firmament ſhews his handy Work.</hi> Now this Light they abuſed and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>improved; they changed the Glory of the incorruptible God, into an Image made like to corruptible Man, and to Birds, and four footed Beaſts, <hi>thus they became vain in their own Imaginations:</hi> For which cauſe God gave <note place="margin">Ver. 24.</note> them up to uncleanneſs, thro' the Luſts of their own Hearts; yea, he gave them up to vile Affections, and to a <hi>reprobate Mind;</hi> or. <note place="margin">Ver. 26.</note> to a mind void of Judgment, to do thoſe things which are not convenient: Now, if ſins againſt the Light of Nature, be of ſuch an aggravating Nature, as to provoke God, to give up Perſons to blindneſs of Mind. What will ſins againſt the Light of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel do? the greater the Light is that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſin againſt, the greater muſt their Sin be, and the more provoking in the Sight of God. Which brings me to the</p>
            <p>Second thing, Namely, ſins againſt the Light of the Goſpel; theſe are great ſin, and provoke God highly to Anger; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject Chriſt, and his Goſpel, and not receive the Love of the Truth, as it in Jeſus, is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37874:12"/> the ready way to be judicially hardened and blinded, and to be given up by the holy God, to <hi>believe Lies,</hi> that we may be damn'd: <note place="margin">2 Theſ 2. 10, 11.</note> If you read the Scriptures in the margent, you will plainly ſee, that Gods judicial <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 14 Mark 4. 12 Acts 28. 26, 27.</note> giving over this People to blindneſs, &amp;c. was conſequent to their ſinful ſtopping of their Ears, ſhutting of their Eyes, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt the light of the Word, &amp; of their own Conſciences received from it: It is dreadful ſinning againſt the Light of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, (which is Gods ſpy, and Mans O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeer) and the Light of the holy Word; for this cauſe many are blinded, and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally hardened by God the Judge of all: God hath given them, (ſays St. <hi>Paul) the Spirit of ſlumber, Eyes that they ſhould not ſee, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 8. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Ears that they ſhould not hear unto this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But who are they, that thus ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Light? The Light of the Word, and of Conſcience, which ſo highly provoke God to anger againſt them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, They are ſuch as ſin after the many Warnings, and Admonitions gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them by God, in his holy Word. God's Trumpet <hi>(viz.</hi> his Word,) is blown in Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ears dayly, which calls them to retreat and break off from ſin: (God ſaith) <hi>My Son, if Sinners intice you,</hi> (if they would <note place="margin">Prov. 1. 10, 11.</note> have partake with them in their Sins) <hi>conſent thou not;</hi> give no way to them, nor to their Temptations; they that ſin with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, muſt look to ſuffer with others in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37874:12"/> their plagues, without true Repentance. They that like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Lovi,</hi> Brethren in Iniquity, ſhall alſo be Brethren in Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Therefore (ſays God) <hi>enter not into the Path of the wicked, go not in the way of evil</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 4. 14. 15. 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Men: Avoid it, paſs not by it, turn from it, and paſs away; for they ſleep not, except they have done Miſchief, and they eat the Bread of Wickedneſs,</hi> &amp;c. Oh! how cautelous is this Caution, to have a Care of ſin, and of being led away by the Wicked into the evil Ways of it: Forſake (ſays God) <hi>the way of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Fooliſh, and walk in the way of Vnderſtanding, and come out from amongſt them; and touch not the unclean thing, and I will receive you, and be your God, and you ſhall be my Sons and Daughters,</hi> ſaith the Lord. Sinners! You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not plead Ignorance, as an Excuſe for your ſins, who live under the Goſpel: You have heard the Word of God preached of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by a many of Gods Servants, which call you to break off Sin by <hi>Repentance;</hi> to plow up the fallow Ground of your Hearts, and not <hi>ſow among Thorns; leſt the Fury of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 4. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Lord come forth like Fire, and none can quench it, becauſe of the evil of your Doings.</hi> The Word calls you to deny all <hi>Ungodlineſs and worldly Luſt; and to live ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>berly, righteouſly and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 11. 12.</note> 
               <hi>godly in this preſent World:</hi> You have (you Wretches) been told often of Sin, and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt it; and yet you will venter upon it: You have been told of your Pride, and Malice, and Swearing, calling God to damn
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37874:13"/> your Souls; and of your Drunkenneſs, and Sabboth-Breaking, and yet you live in theſe <note place="margin">Tim. 3. 13. 1 Tim. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 12.</note> Sins. This is indeed to <hi>ſin againſt Light;</hi> Oh! have a Care, you provoke not God to <hi>give you up to blindneſs of Mind, to deceive and to be deceived.</hi> Flee theſe things, and follow after <hi>Righteouſneſs and Godlineſs, Faith, Patience, Love and Meekneſs:</hi> But,</p>
            <p>2<hi>dly.</hi> Such ſins againſt Light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as Live in the total neglect of thoſe Holy duties, which God calls for, and that they know well, they ſhould be found in the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of: You have been told often, that <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 2. 1 Theſ. 5. 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>you ought to Pray, to continue in Prayer, and to Pray alwayes;</hi> that is, always to have your hearts in a praying frame for <hi>God,</hi> and yet you Live in the neglect of it; there are many prayerleſs perſons, who mind not this Work, which is their priviledge as well as duty: You have been told alſo, that it is your duty to hear <hi>God</hi>'s Word often, and to live the Sermons in your Lives, which you hear with your Ears, out of the Pulpit; and to read the Scriptures much, which are able to make you Wiſe unto Salvation: But Oh! how is this Work neglected by many? if they do hear, and read now and then, they mind it not, but caſt the Word of <hi>God</hi> behind them: What wretches are theſe, not to mind what the Great King of Heaven, and Earth ſays to them: <hi>I have called</hi> (ſays <hi>God) but they have</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 25, 29.</note> 
               <hi>refuſed, and have ſet at nought all my Counſels,</hi> and would not be reprov'd by me; they hate
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37874:13"/> knowledge, and have not choſe the <hi>Lord;</hi> this is matter of Lamentation, and it ſhall be for a Lamentation, that the great God ſhould call after ſorry ſinful man, and he refuſe to hear and regard; Is not this provoking? what will God do to ſuch? Will he let them go unpuniſhed? No, he'll lay his <hi>Ireful Rod</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, <hi>and Laugh when their Calamity comes.</hi> Many are convinc'd, that it is their <note place="margin">Ver. 27. 28.</note> duty to pray in their Families, and yet can go Days, Weeks, and Months without it, and <hi>God</hi> never hear of them. I fear many profeſſors are guilty in this point; let me tell you, in the Name, and Fear of the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>God,</hi> that theſe are dreadful ſins, and a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy way to bring <hi>Gods</hi> Curſe down upon you: Pour out (ſays the Prophet) <hi>thy Fury upon</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 10. ult.</note> 
               <hi>the Heathen, and</hi> the Families, which call not upon thy Name: Here Heathens, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erleſs Families, and Perſons, are reckoned together, as being nothing better than they. Think often upon that word of the <hi>Apoſtle, He that knoweth to do good, and doth it not, to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jam. 4. 18.</note> 
               <hi>him it is a ſin.</hi> But,</p>
            <p>3<hi>dly.</hi> Such perſons ſin greatly againſt Light, that Live in the practiſe of thoſe ſins which they condemn in others; it is the trick of Hypocrites, and wicked Men, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn that in others, which they allow, and practiſe themſelves: But what ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to ſuch kind of men, <hi>Art thou inexcuſeable</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>O man, whoſoever thou art, that Judgeſt? For wherein thou Judgeſt another, thou Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37874:14"/> thy ſelf; for thou that judgeſt, doſt the ſame things.</hi> But we are ſure (ſays he) that the Judgment of God is according to Truth, againſt ſuch, as commit ſuch things; thinkeſt thou this, O man! That judgeſt them which do ſuch things, and doeſt the ſame; that thou ſhalt eſcape the Judgment of God? <hi>Seneca</hi> wrote againſt Superſtitions, and the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, and yet worſhip'd Images himſelf: Many condemn that as ſinful in others, which they allow in themſelves; is not this to ſin againſt Light? Let ſuch perſons have a care, they be not left of God, to blindneſs of Mind, and hardneſs of Heart: One he Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns for Covetouſneſs, and yet he is Covetous; another for Pride, and yet he is Proud; ſuch were theſe in my Text; they ſaid, <hi>men muſt not commit Adultery,</hi> and yet <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 19. 20, <hi>to</hi> 24.</note> they committed Adultery; they pretended <hi>to abhor Idols,</hi> and yet committed Sacriledge: They taught, that a man muſt not Steal, and yet they Stole; ſo, while they boaſted of the Law, they became Tranſgreſſors of it, and Diſhonour'd God: But,</p>
            <p>4<hi>thly.</hi> They ſin againſt Light, that ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the expreſs Threatnings of God in his Word againſt ſin. Hath not God ſaid, that to be ſure your ſins ſhall find you out? i. e. the puniſhments due to you for them. Has not the Lord ſaid expreſly, <hi>that the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 9. 17.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall be turned into Hell, and all the Nations that forget God?</hi> and yet you go on, as if God were but in jeſt, and did not mean as he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37874:14"/> ſpake. God hath thunder'd out his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt Sin, and Sinners; he hath ſaid, <hi>that he will wound the Head of his Enemies, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 68. 21.</note> 
               <hi>the hairy Scalp of him that remaineth ſtill in his ſins:</hi> And yet you go on, and hold your ſins faſt; tho' God ſets the point of the Sword at your Breaſt, yet you will go on in your ſins, and Rebellion againſt him. Is not this (think you) to ſin againſt Light? doth not this argue that the pleaſures of ſin doth: more delight and pleaſe you, than the Threatnings of God afright you? Are not many ſinners <hi>like the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathan,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job. 41. 29.</note> that Laughs at the ſhaking of the ſpear? many Laugh when they hear of <hi>Hell,</hi> but they will not when they come there; there be many ſo bold, that they deride Gods threatnings; they ſay as them (who draw Iniquity with Cords of Vanity) <hi>Let him</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 5. 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>make ſpeed, and haſten his work, that we may ſee it,</hi> &amp;c. As if they had ſaid, we have heard that God will do much againſt ſinners, and that his Judgments will Light upon them: Why do not he do it? We would fain ſee it.</p>
            <p>Let the Counſel of the Holy One of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> draw nigh and come, that we may know it. What wretches are theſe, thus to deride Gods threatnings! Let ſuch vile ones re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this, that for men to ſee Gods Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Sword as it were, drawn againſt ſin and ſinners, and yet ſtrengthen themſelves in ſin, is to ſin againſt Light and Knowledg, and the way highly to provoke God.</p>
            <p>But Laſtly, ſuch ſin indeed againſt Light,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37874:15"/> as ſin after many Promiſes, and Vows made againſt it. How many have promiſed God fairly, to amend and leave ſin, and yet they go on in it? What ſays <hi>Solomon</hi> to ſuch? <hi>When thou voweſt a vow unto God, defer not to pay it: For he hath no pleaſure in fools; pay that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 5. 4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>which thou haſt vow'd: Better is it, that thou ſhouldeſt not vow, than that thou ſhouldeſt vow, and not pay: Suffer not thy Mouth to cauſe thy Fleſh to ſin,</hi> &amp;c. Many put God off, with a many good morrows, and fair promiſes to Repent, and amend their-ways, but mind not to perform'em. A Vow is a religious promiſe <note place="margin">What a Vow is,</note> made to God, to dedicate our ſelves to him, and to be for him, and for no other but him. Now, how greatly do they ſin, that have not only purpoſed, but promiſed to leave ſin, and yet they Live in it? Every man that vows, makes himſelf a debtor; he binds himſelf to God, in a ſolemn manner: Now for a man to ſin after a vow, to vow himſelf to God, and yet give himſelf to Sin, and the Devil, is to ſin againſt Light, with a witneſs. Let men have a care what they do in this point, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially profeſſors, who have the vows of <hi>God</hi> upon them. It is dangerous to Leave God, when we have vow'd our ſelves to him: Thus much for the firſt general.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> I ſhall now lay down a few propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for the better clearing of the Doctrine; and they are, theſe ſix following, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt Prop.</hi> That God ſometimes puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth ſin, with ſin; for ſin, he gives men up of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37874:15"/> to be led Capuve by their baſe Luſts. <hi>God gave them up</hi> (ſays <hi>Paul) to uncleanneſs,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 24, 26.</note> 
               <hi>thro' the Luſt that were in their Hearts.</hi> When men harden their hearts willfully, God often hardens them judicially: <hi>Pharaoh would not let</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 7. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>the People go:</hi> Well (ſays God) with he not let my Son go to ſerve me? <hi>I will Harden his Heart, that he ſhall not let them go,</hi> &amp;c. They that will not Repent when God would have them, but harden their Hearts, and ſay they will do ſo again, ſhall not have a Heart, nor Grace to Repent to purpoſe; when for Fear of Judgements, they with <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſeek a place for Repentance. It is a dreadful Judgment, for God to Puniſh ſin with ſin. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Spiritual Judgments, of all, on this <note place="margin">Prop. 2.</note> ſide <hi>Hell,</hi> are the worſt; a Judicial Blindneſs of Mind, and Hardneſs of Heart, (of all <note place="margin">Rev. 22. 17 Hoſ. 4. 19.</note> Plagues) are the worſt. For God to ſay, <hi>Let him that is Filthy, be Filthy still, and he that is Unjuſt, be Unjuſt ſtill,</hi> is very dreadful. Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſtrive not with him any more, he is joyn'd to <hi>Idols,</hi> let him alone: What can be more dreadful on this ſide <hi>Hell,</hi> than for God to ſay <note place="margin">Ez.. 24. 13.</note> to Sinners, becauſe when <hi>I have Purged thee, thou waſt not Purged; thou ſhalt not be Purged from thy Filthineſs, till I cauſe my Fury to reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee?</hi> Spiritual Judgments, and Plagues, are the worſt, and that for theſe three Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt Reaſon is, in reſpect the Subject up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom they Fall; and that is the <hi>Soul</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16. 26.</note> is a rare, and precious Jewel. The <hi>Soul</hi> of Man is worth more than all the World; for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37874:16"/> the World cannot with all its Riches, ſave, nor redeem it. The <hi>Soul</hi> is a ſpiritual ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in Man, Created by God the Father of <hi>Spirits,</hi> which can exiſt, when ſeparated from the <hi>Body.</hi> Now, by how much the <hi>Soul</hi> 
               <note place="margin">What the Soul is. Ecc. 12. 7.</note> is better than the <hi>Body,</hi> by ſo much muſt it be worſe; for the <hi>Soul</hi> to be afflicted, as mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to the <hi>Soul,</hi> are the greateſt, ſo judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon it, muſt be the greateſt. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Becauſe theſe plagues are the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Evidences of Eternal Wrath; What ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer mark for Hell can there be than this? for a Perſon judicially to be left of God here, <note place="margin">John 3. 36.</note> and given up <hi>to Blindneſs of Mind, to believe Lies,</hi> is a ſure mark of eternal ruine, and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> Spiritual judgments are the worſt, becauſe they hinder, and with-hold from us the beſt good, which is <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt:</hi> Now that which reſtrains and keeps from us the beſt, and chief good, (without which our <hi>Souls</hi> cannot be happy) muſt needs be the worſt kinds of reſtraints, and judgments: What plagues are like thoſe of Hardneſs of Heart, a Spirit of ſlumber, taking away the gifts of the Mind, and giving men over to the power of <hi>Satan,</hi> and to the love of Sin, with-holding that good by the Goſpel, which our <hi>Souls</hi> need, and others in mercy enjoy? But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> The ſins of a Perſon and People, may provoke God to curſe their very Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, <note place="margin">Prop. 3.</note> and cauſe thoſe things which are Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37874:16"/> in themſelves, to prove Judgments to them: As for inſtance, Rain is a great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; to have <hi>the former, and the latter Rain in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 5. 24.</note> 
               <hi>its Seaſon,</hi> is no ſmall Bleſſing: Yet how has ſin turn'd this into a Judgment to many? In every drop of Rain, <hi>there is an Ocean of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 42. 21, 26.</note> 
               <hi>Wiſdom, Goodneſs and Mercy;</hi> but ſin often makes it a Judgement to many: Fire is a Mercy; Yet how often for ſin has it been ſent in a way of Judgement; it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and laid them in <note place="margin">Mark 9. 43.</note> Aſhes for their ſins. How many dreadful Fires hath ſin kindled in this Nation and City? And there is one Fire kindled by it, that will never go out, and <hi>that is the Fire of Hell?</hi> &amp;c. To have the Goſpel, is a great Mercy; <hi>but how ſhall we eſcape,</hi> (if we refuſe to hear Chriſt, that ſpeaketh in it) <hi>and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 3, 12 25.</note> 
               <hi>ſo great a Salvation:</hi> Sin provokes God to curſe our bleſſings, and turn them into Judgements. <hi>If ye will not hear, and if ye</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>will not lay it to heart, to give Glory unto my Name, (ſaith the Lord of Hoſt) I will even ſend a curſe upon you; and I will curſe your Bleſſings; yea, I have curſed them already, becauſe ye do not lay it to Heart.</hi> Here is the Cauſe of the Curſe, and it is a Cauſe ſo juſt, (as they upon whom it falls) have no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to complain of Gods too ſevere proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt them. God (beloved) is the Author and Inflicter of all Judgements; he ſends his Curſe for ſin, but eſpecially for <note place="margin">Amos 6 3.</note> Corruptions in Religion, and Contempt of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37874:17"/> his holy Word. When God's Word and Goſpel is heard and preached, it muſt be <note place="margin">Prov. 13. 13. Jam. 1. 22, 23. Pſ, 119. 9. Luke 2. 19 Heb. 6. 8.</note> attended upon, and obeyed. For without this, Hearing is counted no hearing; we had as good not hear, as not lay the <hi>Word</hi> to our hearts, and practice it in our lives. God's word muſt be hid in our Hearts, and Chriſts ſayings muſt be pondered there, or elſe we hear not to purpoſe. Careleſs and fruitleſs Hearers are nigh unto Curſing, whoſe end <hi>(Paul</hi> tells us) is at laſt dying ſo, <hi>to be burned:</hi> But,</p>
            <p>Fouthly, From one and the ſame Cauſe, may ariſe divers and contrary Effects; that <note place="margin">Prop. 4.</note> which ſoftens one, may harden another; that which enlightens one, may be a means to blind another. Chriſt that is a Stone of Foundation to a believer, is a Stone of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to the Unbeliever. The Goſpel of Peace, <note place="margin">Mat. 3. 12. 2 Cor. 2. 15, 16.</note> and glad Tidings to a wicked Man, <hi>is a fire, a ſword and a fan;</hi> but to the godly, it is <hi>a ſavour of Life,</hi> and a means to bring' em to God thro' Chriſt, and to Salvation. As the Sun melteth the wax, and hardneth the clay; ſo the Goſpel accidentally (by the corruption that is in wicked men, and by the fearful Judgements of God) hardens and blinds them, while others are ſoftned, and made anew by it. The Goſpel to ſome is the Power of God, but to others a Stone of <hi>ſtumbling,</hi> and very fooliſhneſs. The Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel <note place="margin">1 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 23, 24.</note> that is a bleſſing to ſome, (thro' ſin and unbelief) proves a Judgement to many. Oh!</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:37874:17"/>
            <p>Let Perſons have a care, that they do not reſt in the having barely the means of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the preaching of the Word, &amp;c. It is a Mercy indeed, to enjoy the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; but it is not to be reſted in by any; for thro' their Corruption and Sin, it may be a greater means of Damnation: Bleſs God for the means of Grace, be thankful to him for his holy Word; but be ſure you be not ſatisfied, without the Grace of means, <hi>leſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 16.</note> 
               <hi>you be blinded,</hi> &amp;c. Say, when you go to hear the Word preached, Lord, let it be thy power, to the ſaving of my poor Soul: But,</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The Judgements which fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Prop. 5.</note> particular wicked men, for their Sins and Unbelief, are to be accounted the Puniſhments of the whole Body of Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. This Judgement of Blindneſs in our Text, which hapned to many of the Jews and Phariſees, for their rejecting Chriſt and his Goſpel, is the Puniſhment of all Perſons, that ſhall be found ſuch Offenders: And that for four Reaſons,</p>
            <p>Becauſe all the Judgements that ſell upon <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> them (for their rejecting Chriſt, and ſtumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at him) all wicked men have, and do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve: Are not they worthy of the ſame Strokes, and of the ſame Judgements, that ſlight the ſame Chriſt, and trample upon the ſame Blood and Goſpel, which they did? What ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to this? If they (ſays he) <hi>that deſpiſed</hi> Moſes's Law, dyed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37874:18"/> 
               <hi>without Mercy, &amp;c. Of how much forer Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments ſhall they be thought worthy, who have</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 28.</note> 
               <hi>trodden under Foot the Son of God, and have counted the Blood of the Covenant an unholy thing?</hi> &amp;c. Surely, ſuch Wretches cannot think at laſt, to eſcape the deſerved Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, who undervalue Chriſt, and trample upon his Blood and Merits: <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 30.</note> 
               <hi>is mine</hi> (ſays God) <hi>and I will repay it.</hi> I will eaſe me of mine Adverſaries, and be avenged on all them, that deſpiſe my Son, and caſt my Word behind them. Oh! Let Sinners hear and tremble, and lay this <note place="margin">Ver. 31. Pſal. 2. 12.</note> to heart, <hi>that'tis a fearful thing, to fall into the bands of an angry God: For while his Wrath is kindled but a little; bleſſed are they that truſt in him:</hi> But ſecondly,</p>
            <p>Becauſe when God threatens ſome, he <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> threatens all, that are ſuch groſs Offenders: As the Promiſes run general to all that repent and believe in Chriſt; ſo the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings run to all that are, and ſhall be found at laſt Rejecters of Chriſt, and his Word. Were the Jews and Phariſees blinded, who ſtumbled at Chriſt, and his precious Word? Were they offended becauſe of him, and ſo were cut off, and puniſhed for their Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief? So ſhall all as are offended at Chriſt and his Word, and ſhall at laſt be found Unbelievers; for as <hi>he that believeth ſhall be ſaved,</hi> and not at laſt confounded; ſo, he <note place="margin">Mar. 16. 16. 1 Pet. 2. 6.</note> 
               <hi>that believeth not ſhall be damned.</hi> Chriſt, the Judge of all, will come at laſt in <hi>ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37874:18"/> Fire</hi> (that is, in a terrible Manner) <hi>to take Vengeance on them that know not God, and obey not his Goſpel, who ſhall be puniſhed with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ 1. 7, &amp; 9.</note> 
               <hi>everlaſting Deſtruction from the Preſence of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. Let all Perſons have a Care (Young and Old, Rich and Poor) they be not found at laſt Rejecters of Chriſt, and his Goſpel. For remember, that the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments inflicted others, God means to you; <hi>Who ſo deſpiſeth the Word,</hi> (let him <note place="margin">Prov. 13. 13.</note> be who he will, and as great as he will) <hi>ſhall be deſtroyed:</hi> it is not ſaid, they may, but they ſhall be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> Becauſe no ungodly Men in the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> World, can be ſure for the time to come, that they ſhall not fall upon him. What Aſſurance have you, O Sinners, who live in ſin and deſpiſe the Word! that you (who think you ſee, and boaſt of your Knowledge) ſhall not be blinded and <hi>turned into Hell,</hi> as <note place="margin">Pſalm 9. 17. Mat. 24. 48. <hi>to the end.</hi>
               </note> others for their Diſobedience and Unbelief are. Doth not the word of the holy God ſay, that all the wicked ſhall be <hi>turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell?</hi> and are you ſure this ſhall not be your Portion? Were theſe wretches in my Text, blinded for their Unbelief, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing dear Jeſus and his precious word? And are you ſure (Sinners!) that this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will not fall upon you, if you thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to ſin, and reject the Grace of the Goſpel? Have many for their ſins, (as a juſt Judgement from God) been blinded and damned by the Word, which have been a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37874:19"/> means thro' Grace, to ſave others? Oh! Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er this, <hi>you that forget God, leſt he tear</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal 50. 21, 22, Prov. 29. 1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>you in Pieces, and there be none to deliver you.</hi> Remember what the word ſaith, that he, <hi>who is often reproved, and yet hardens his neck, ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed, and that without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.</hi> But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4dly.</hi> It is thus, becauſe the Judgements <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> in this Life, are typical to wicked men. Of what (if they die in Unbelief and Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt Chriſt and his word) ſhall be their Portion in the next? Deſpair to a wicked man is a typical Hell, (for Hell is a Place of eternal deſpair) and ſo all other Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Judgements here, are but little Hells. Let Sinners tremble at this, who are Rejecters of Chriſt, and take unjuſtly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at his word. Oh! You wretches, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 21.</note> this, that any fearful Judgements that fall upon others for their ſins, may fall up: on you; and that God is as well diſpleaſed with your ſins, as with thoſe that he has plagued, and ſent to Hell; this our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord Jeſus tells you is a truth. Think ye (ſays Chriſt,) <hi>That they upon whom the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 13. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Tower of</hi> Siloam <hi>fell, and ſlew them, that they were ſinners above all men that dwelt in</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem? Were there none in that City to be parallelled with them for their ſins? <hi>I tell you, except ye repent, you ſhall all likewiſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh:</hi> It is no matter what Sinners they were, if you do not repent, and leave your ſins, you ſhall all periſh as well as they: But ſo much for the fifth Propoſition.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:37874:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>6thly.</hi> God by Chriſt is juſt and righteous, <note place="margin">Prop. 6.</note> in this diſpenſation of his, in cauſing ſome to ſee, and others by the ſame means, to be hardened and made blind. None ſhall have ought to ſay againſt him at the Laſt day; but all then ſhall be made to ſay, <hi>Righteous art</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 12. 1.</note> 
               <hi>thou O Lord.</hi> Chriſt will have enough to lay to the Charge of wicked Men, for their reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of Him, and the tenders of his Grace to them, in and by his Word. But their Mouths ſhall then be all ſtopp'd &amp; muzzled; for none ſhall enter into Judgment with God, nor have <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 12.</note> any thing to ſay for themſelves, nor againſt God: Some now ſay, that God will not turn them, &amp; that he has reprobated them to Hell; and if they pine away in their Sins, how con they help it? Thus many quarrel with God here, but no ſuch complaints ſhall <note place="margin">Ez. 33. 10, 11.</note> be heard againſt God at the Laſt day; for then all ſinners ſhall ſee that their Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is Juſt, and ſo ſhall clear God, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Condemn themſelves. One will ſay, (when in Hell) God is Juſt in ſending of me hither, for by my ſins I have deſerved to come to this place of Torments. Another will ſay, my Pride hath brought me hither; another, my Swearing and Prodigality; a third, my Unbelief, and rejecting of Chriſt, and his Word, has ſunk me into this abyſs of miſery. Oh! What complaints will ſinners make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves? How will they reiterate again and again thoſe good Sermons, and wholeſome Inſtructions they have heard, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37874:20"/> miſimprov'd here on earth? each one will ſay, <hi>How have I hated Inſtruction, and my Heart deſpiſed reproof; and have not Obey'd the ways of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 4. 11, 12, 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>my Teachers, nor Inclined my Ear to them that Inſtructed me.</hi> The Lord (will every one then ſay) is Juſt and Righteous, in ſending me here to this place of endleſs, and eaſleſs Miſery: For by my ſins, I have deſerved it a Thouſand times over. Thus much for the Propoſitions:</p>
            <p>I ſhall now <hi>3dly,</hi> ſhew you, how this ſtands with the Holyneſs and Kindneſs of God, <hi>to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3d. Head 2 Theſ. 2. 10, u.</note> 
               <hi>give Men up to Blindneſs of Mind and Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart, to believe Lyes</hi> (that as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle</hi> ſays) they may be damned.</p>
            <p>This I muſt confeſs, ſounds harſh at the firſt, and ſeems to be Inconſiſtent with that goodneſs and kindneſs, that God hath expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in his Word to ſinner: But I hope anon, you will ſee clearly, that in theſe tremendous diſpenſations, God is both Good and Juſt. Before I ſpeak directly to this caſe, I ſhall premiſe two things, that will give you great Light in this matter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that God in all his diſpenſations of Grace and Providence, acts in a way of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty <note place="margin">Prem 1.</note> like himſelf, as not being bound to his Creatures: He hath Mercy on whom he will have Mercy; and whom he will, he hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. Why doth God write ſome Names in <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 18.</note> the Book of Life, and leave out others? Why doth he ſave ſome, and Condemn others at laſt? Why are ſome Enlightned, and others Blinded by the ſame Word? Why doth not
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37874:20"/> God Accompany it with the Efficacy, of his Spirit in ſome, as well as in others? What (beloved) will you reſolve theſe things into, but the Soveraign Will and Pleaſure of God, <hi>Who giveth no Account of his matters</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job. 33. 13.</note> 
               <hi>unto any?</hi> Why are ſome Rich and others Poor? ſome Noble, and others Ignoble? ſome Strong and Healthy, and others Sickly and Weakly? &amp;c. Why, it is the Will and Pleaſures of God it ſhould be ſo. God giveth Grace when and to whom he pleaſes, as well as other things. Why doth not God mould the Heart to a Goſpel frame, when he fills the Ear with a Goſpel ſound? Why are not all Converted by the Word, as well as ſome? Why doth God ſtrike off the Chains from ſome, and tear off the Veil from the Heart; while he leaves others in Slavery, and Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian darkneſs? Why do ſome ly under the bands of Death, while others are raiſed to ſpiritual Life? There is no reaſon for theſe things, but the Soveraign Will of the Great God, <hi>who worketh in us both to will, and to do,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 13.</note> 
               <hi>of his own good pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, tho' God Blinds ſome, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <note place="margin">Prem. 2.</note> others to See, Save ſome and Condemn others; ſoften ſome by the word, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens others by it; yet <hi>he is Juſt and Righteous.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 25.</note> Shall not the Judge of all the Earth do right? Yea ſurely, he that is all righteouſneſs cannot Act contrary to himſelf, tho' God doth terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things in the way of his providence, yet he doth them all in Righteouſneſs; <hi>He is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 65. 5.</note>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:37874:21"/> 
               <hi>in all his Ways, and holy in all his Works,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 145. 17.</note> 
               <hi>both in his Works of Judgement, as well as Mercy.</hi> He that Acts in a way of Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (remember it) always Acts in a way of perfect Righteouſneſs and Equity. Who can charge God with ſin, and ſay that he is not Juſt and Righteous in what he doth? Oh! be ſure, that in all things you acknowledge God to be Juſt, tho' you underſtand not well the reaſon of things done by him: Remember tho' you may want a reaſon for Gods dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in the World, yet he hath alwayes a reaſon for what he doth; and that is his Will, which is the Rule of Perfection, and the ſupream Reaſon. <hi>He worketh all things according to the Councel of his own</hi> Will, that <note place="margin">Eph. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 12. Mat. 11. 25. 26.</note> the Myſteries of the Goſpel are revealed to Babes, and hid from the Wiſe and Learned ones of the Age, is from Gods Will, who Acteth Righteouſly in all he doth: Inquire not then, into the reaſon of Gods Will, but ſubmit your ſelves to it: Say not, why are ſome ſoftned, and others hardned; ſome elected, and others reprobated; ſome ſaved, and others damned? Remember that God is Good and Juſt; tho' the manner of God's dealings, may ſometimes be hidden, yet it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is, nor can be unjuſt: If God reprobate ſinners, it is becauſe it agreeth with their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervings; and if he elects the ſinful, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it agrees with his goodneſs: So that, be ſure you retain this as a great Truth, that God is Righteous in all he doth: Let
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37874:21"/> God be true (ſays the <hi>Apoſtle)</hi> but every man a Lyar. Having thus premiſed theſe two things, I ſhall now come to the point, and ſhew you how this ſtands with the holineſs and kindneſs of God, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That I may clear and open this to you, we muſt firſt conſider what God doth in the tremendous diſpenſations, of blinding ſome by that means, by which others in Mercy are made to ſee; this I ſhall ſpeak to theſe two ways, <hi>viz. 1ſt.</hi> By way of Negation, <hi>2dly.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> I ſhall ſpeak to it Negatively, and ſhew you what God doth not: In theſe 3 things,</p>
            <p>Firſt, when God is ſaid to blind or harden any, he doth not Infuſe any malice into their <note place="margin">James. 1. 44. 18.</note> Hearts: To aſſert this, were to make God the Author of ſin, which he is not. He is the Author of all Good, and of his own Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but not of ſin; for he tempteth no man to Evil. The Papiſts and the <hi>Arminians</hi> brand us with this falſly, of making God the Author of ſin, which we abhor. All that we ſay is this, that the Holy God, is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all his own Judgements: When God judicially blinds or hardens any, he doth not put nor excite malice in them: Sin is the <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 44. 18.</note> 
               <hi>thing</hi> that God hates; therefore he cannot be the Author of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> This blinding, &amp;c. is not by the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of God only, in ſparing to puniſh ſinners for their ſins: In this ſenſe, wicked men are ſaid to blind and harden themſelves,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37874:22"/> in the abuſe of Gods long ſuffering and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us of ſome <hi>who thro' the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Hearts deſpiſed the goodneſs, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>long forbearance of God, which leadeth to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;</hi> and ſo they treaſured up Wrath, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the day of Wrath, and the revelation of the Righteous Judgement of God; God in this ſenſe (beloved) is not ſaid to blind any; but as ſinners are ſaid to blind and harden themſelves by his Patience and Goodneſs to <note place="margin">Eccles. 8. 11.</note> them. Some ſin becauſe Grace abounds, and are the more ſinful, becauſe God is kind to them, and patient with them. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> This blinding, &amp;c. is not by bear permiſſion only, as ſome think and aſſert: God blinds and hardens; that is, he permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and ſuffereth ſinners to be hardened, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſome, &amp;c. 'Tis true, there is Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in this diſpenſation; but you muſt know, that there is more than that in this action. Permiſſion in the ſenſe of ſome Men, doth ſuppoſe God either to be idle, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, or againſt his will to ſuffer things to be done in the World. To aſſert this, is to caſt upon the Great God,</p>
            <p>Firſt, an imputation of negligence, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence; as Old <hi>Eli</hi> permitted his Sons to ſin; that is, Indulged them in their ſins. But who dare be ſo bold, as to charge God with Negligence, or Indulgence, who is alwayes Ruling, and Over-ruling all things in the World for his own Glory? <hi>His Throne is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 103. 9.</note> 
               <hi>prepared in the Heavens, and his Kingdom Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth over all.</hi> But,</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:37874:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Of impotency, in permitting things which he cannot hinder. If <hi>God</hi> (beloved) only barely permitteth this, then it is either by way of Indulgence, or for want of Power to prevent it; but it is not from either of theſe, therefore there is more than <hi>God,</hi> bare permiſſion in it. Beloved, <hi>God</hi> is ſaid Seven or eight times over, to harden <hi>Pharoahs</hi> heart; and it is obſervable, that the words which the Scripture maketh uſe of, to ſignify <hi>Gods</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 4. 21. 7. 3. 10. 3.</note> penal action in blinding ſinners, are ſuch, as cannot be expounded by a bare permiſſion, or diſſertion only. <hi>God</hi> in theſe tremendous diſpenſations, (acting as a Judge by way of puniſhment) muſt Act not meerly privitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but poſitively: And I prove it this way; namely, that an Inſliction of Puniſhment al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways argues a poſitive Judgement of <hi>God;</hi> he Acteth as a Judge in it, and therefore muſt do ſomething poſitively. We need not be over ſolicitous and curious, to examin the manner how <hi>God</hi> Acteth; for whither we be able, or not able to open the manner, &amp;c. <hi>God</hi> is Juſt and Righteous in it: Wheu <hi>God</hi> giveth perſons over to vile affections, and a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate mind, as Acts of Puniſhment; he doth it always by a Juſt, tho' it be by a ſecret provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; ſo, that tho' his ways are ſometimes in the Deep, that we cannot well ſearch them out, yet they are never unjuſt. Thus you ſee in ſhort, that <hi>God</hi> doth more than permit this, &amp;c. for he is the Author of his own Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us (ſpeaking of the Jews)
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37874:23"/> 
               <hi>that God hath given them the Spirit of ſlumber</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. II. 7, 8, 10, 11.</note> (not as it is a ſin) but as it is a Judgement, which he is Author of, and yet moſt Juſt and Righteous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur. <hi>2dly.</hi> by way of affirmation in theſe three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, when God doth judicially blind Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and give them over to believe Lies, &amp;c. he doth undoubtedly withdraw thoſe means which ſhould enlighten their Minds, and keep them effectually from the reigning Power of their Luſts. God doth not harden and blind by imparting Malice, or putting Hardneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Heart; but by withholding or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing that means and grace, that ſhould ſoften and enlighten. Now, is God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous in this? ſurely no; (for as Chriſt ſaith) he may do what he will with his own: <note place="margin">Matt. 20. 15.</note> Had not God withheld his Grace from the Angels, and from our firſt Parents, (ſaith a learned Man) the firſt had not fallen from their glorious ſtate, nor the ſecond from their ſtate of Innocency; by which (ſays he) <note place="margin">D. E. on Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> it appears, that this is no more than God might have done, if man had not ſinned, &amp;c. To ſay the contrary, is to make God a debtor to the Creature, which he is not; who can ſay, God owed him any thing? We are debtors to him, but he is not to us; he gives, or withholds his grace, when and to whom he pleaſes, and none muſt, nor dare ſay to him, what doſt thou? All the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Earth are reputed as nothing, <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 35.</note> and he doth according to his Will in the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37874:23"/> Army of Heaven, and among the Inhabitants <note place="margin">Job. 9. 12. Iſa. 45. 9. Jer. 18. 6. 7.</note> of the Earth, and none can ſtay his Hand, or ſay to him, what doſt thou? Behold! he taketh away, who can hinder him, who will ſay unto him, what doſt thou? But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> When God judicially blinds Perſons, he delivers them up to the power of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, to be more blinded, ſeduced and harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; he ſuffers them to be led away captive by the devil at his will: The Lord thus blinds many, by giving them up to the power of Satan, for him to work upon; thus wicked <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ahab</hi> were harden'd, and thoſe mentioned in 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 10. 11. Satan ſeduceth Souls by command from the holy God, as appeareth in the ſtory of wicked <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab;</hi> the Lord hath put <hi>a lying ſpirit in the month of all</hi> theſe thy <hi>Prophets,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The God</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 22. 22. 23. 2 Cor. 4. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>of this World</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) hath blinded the minds of them that believe not,</hi> &amp;c. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> When God blinds and hardens Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons judicially, he leaves them to the <hi>Impetus</hi> and force of their Luſts and Corruptions: Thus God hardens them by themſelves, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them up to the power of their own Luſts: <hi>He gave the Heathens up to vile Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 26.</note> 
               <hi>and permitted them to ſin yet more and more;</hi> proud <hi>Pharoah</hi> by his ſin and own free-will, hardened his heart, and God har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened <note place="margin">Exo 1. 4. 21, 22.</note> it by his Judgements, giving him up to his Luſts. This (Beloved) is a general way of God in this diſpenſation; for all that periſh, are thus left to themſelves, to act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37874:24"/> to the <hi>Impetus</hi> of that original Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and Luſt that is in their hearts. Now none can deny, but this is conſiſtent with the Juſtice and Kindneſs of God: For if Gods leaving and ſuffering men to walk in their own ways, not quenching the original Luſt that is in their Hearts, but ſuffering them to put it forth in actual Wickedneſs: I ſay, if Gods doing this, would make him the Author of ſin, then he muſt be concluded to be the Author of all ſin that is committed in the World. But that he is not, <hi>for Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs proceedeth from the Wicked;</hi> as ſaith <note place="margin">1 Sam. 24. 13.</note> the Proverb of the Antients: The word of God telleth us, that he will have Mercy on whom he will; and his Grace could not be Grace, were it not free. Now, pray conſider, Man being by the Fall a ſinner, and full of Corruption, and ſo juſtly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of eternal Death, <hi>(for by one mans Sin, Judgement hath paſſed upon all men to Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and the Wages of Sin is death.</hi> I ſay, it being thus, &amp;c. God is not unjuſt in ſaving ſome, and leaving others to the Force of their own Luſts, when for ſin he might have damned all. I hope there is none will doubt, but that if a Traytor juſtly deſerved to die, and to be ſtarved to death, (tho' the Prince had it in his Power to Pardon, or ſupply him with Bread to keep him from dying in this manner; Yet the Prince were juſt if he did neither, but ſuffered him to periſh according to his deſerts. Surely,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37874:24"/> then God is not unjuſt in ſo doing, ſince all men are Traytors and deſerve to die eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally: This as I think, is denied by none; but that which is greatly diſputed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted by learned Men, is, whether God in blinding Sinners, doth not act ſomething poſitively. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and the <hi>Arminians</hi> deny this in oppoſition to whom, our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines (not without good ground) ſay this, <hi>viz.</hi> That tho' God doth not poſitively blind, or harden any Sinners, yet he doth ſome poſitive Acts, that relate to the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them; 'tis true, God doth not poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively harden any, i. e. he doth not make their ſoft Hearts hard, nor ſhut their Eyes, and of ſeeing, maketh them blind: This, (I ſay) God doth not, yet he is not a meer Spectator, or an idle Looker on, upon the Works of his Providence. In all Acts of Puniſhments, God doth ſomething poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The Scripture ſpeaks of him, as giving up ſome men to vile Affections, and to a reprobate Mind, as Acts of Puniſhment; therefore God, as to them, doth ſomething poſitively, tho' he poſitively hardens none.</p>
            <p>The Sum of all then, in ſhort, is this; God may judicially give many up to their Luſts and to <hi>Satan,</hi> to be ſeduced at his Pleaſure, and be righteous in it. But he cannot puniſh the former ſins of any, by putting any Luſt or Malice into their hearts, by which they become more evil and vile. This I ſay, God cannot do any otherwiſe,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:37874:25"/> than accidentally, ſtirring up that Luſt and Malice that is in their hearts: This is the Sum (as far as I know) of what our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines ſay, as to Gods Acts in the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Sin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Blindneſs then in ſhort, is cauſed, <hi>1st.</hi> By the Word occaſionally. <hi>2dly.</hi> By his own Malice meritoriouſly. <hi>3dly.</hi> By the Devil efficiently. And laſtly, by God judicially. So that Satan is the Tormentor, ſinful Man the guilty Perſon, and the holy God the Judge. Thus far we have ſeen, ſo far as we are able to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend of what God doth by Chriſt, in this Act of puniſhing Sin with Sin, and how juſt and righteous he is in it. We ſhall now,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> Conſider the Circumſtances thoſe <note place="margin">2 Bron. <hi>of the Anſwer.</hi>
               </note> are under, whom God bringeth under ſuch a ſevere diſpenſation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> Theſe Perſons whom God in a way of Juſtice thus deals with, are not only ſinners; <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 23. 1 Pet. 2. 9.</note> (for God doth not deal thus ſeverely with every ſinner) all are ſinners againſt God; but all are not blind and hardened ſinners; ſome are enlightened and called out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into marvellous light: Therefore,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> Theſe ſinners thus blinded, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are ſuch as have provoked the Moſt High to a very great degree, ſhutting their eyes againſt the Light which ſhined upon them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the means which he uſed to reclaim them; ſuch a Wretch was proud <hi>Pharoah:</hi> firſt he hardened his heart, and blinded his <note place="margin">Exod. 7. 3. 4.</note> own mind, and then God ſaid, as a juſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37874:25"/> puniſhment upon him) that he would <hi>har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den his heart,</hi> &amp;c. Such Wretches were the Heathens mentioned by <hi>Paul,</hi> they ſinned prodigiouſly againſt the Light of Nature, for which, God (in a way of judgment, as have been hinted) gave them up to Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 28.</note> thro' the Luſts of their own hearts, and to a reprobate mind, to do thoſe things which were not convenient: Theſe People in my Text mentioned, had ſinned greatly againſt Light, and trampled upon Chriſt, and his Righteouſneſs; therefore God in a way of juſt Judgment upon them for their monſtrous wickedneſs, ſuffered them to be blinded, while others in mercy were brought into Chriſt, and ſavingly enlightned.</p>
            <p>Now (beloved) this being rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, I appeal to all your Conſciences that hear me this day, That (tho' this be a moſt tremendous Diſpenſation of God) yet whether it be not very conſiſtent, both with the Holineſs, Juſtice and Kindneſs of God. What do you think, is it not juſt with God to puniſh Sinners, to avenge him of his Adverſaries? Eſpecially ſuch, as have wilfully ſhut their eyes, leſt the Light of the Goſpel ſhould ſhine upon them, and they ſhould convert, and Chriſt heal them: What ſaith Chriſt of ſuch wretches, <hi>I ſpoke to them in Parables, in dark ſayings, becauſe in ſeeing they ſee not, and in hearing they hear</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 13, 14, 15</note> 
               <hi>not, neither do they underſtand: This Peoples heart is waxed groſs, and their Ears are dull</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:37874:26"/> 
               <hi>of hearing, and their eyes they have cloſed; leſt at any time they ſhould ſee with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and ſhould underſtand with their hearts, and be converted, and I ſhould heal them.</hi> Such Sinners as theſe, you will ſay, deſerved to be puniſhed, and ſent to Hell for their abominable wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Now if it be juſt and righteous in God, to turn ſuch Rebels into Hell for their Sins; Why ſhould it not be juſt in him, to ſeal them up now to that Damnation? Why may not God leave ſuch deſtitute of his Grace, and give them over to a reprobate Mind, and to a hard Heart, and yet be juſt and righteous? Are there any of you that doubt, whether this be conſiſtent with the Goodneſs and Holineſs of God? Let me ask you this one Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May not God deny the means of grace, to whom he pleaſeth, and yet be a holy and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>
               </label> a righteous God? you will ſay Yes; For he is not bound to give it to any. Why then, may not God deny it to, and withdraw it from them in Judgement, that have abuſed his patience, and turned the Doctrine of Grace into wantonneſs? Doth God give up men to <hi>Satan,</hi> and to their Luſts to be ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and hardned? Are not theſe his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in puniſhing Sinners? And may not the juſt and holy God, uſe what Inſtruments he pleaſe, for the Execution of his wrath for Sin? But here you will multiply Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt what I have ſaid, which I ſhall briefly Anſwer.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:37874:26"/>
            <p>Some of you will ſay, Is not Blindneſs of <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>1</label> Mind, and Hardneſs of Heart, Sin? How then can the holy God blind and harden a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and not be the Author of ſin?</p>
            <p>Hardneſs and Blindneſs is not of God, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>1</label> ſimply, or as it is ſin; but only accidental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as it is the Puniſhment of ſin: If Sin be conſidered in its ſelf in its true Nature, as it is a Defect, and a Tranſgreſſion of Gods <note place="margin">1. John 3. 4.</note> holy and righteous Law; ſurely none can be the Author of it, but he that doth it, and perſwades and invites to the doing of it. <note place="margin">James 1. 14. 15</note> Now God, he neither doeth evil, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth, nor infuſeth that Luſt and Sin, that is exerciſed and committed by ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men; therefore he is not the Author of it: But if you conſider ſin, as the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſin, ſo the Permiſſion of it, is but a juſt Diſpenſation of God, and a judicial Act. Now, ſurely, God may be the Author of his own Judgements, without being the Author of Sin: But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> You muſt know, that there is a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between Hardneſs and Hardning, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ </seg>2</label> Blindneſs and Blinding; Blindneſs and Hardineſs is a ſin; but to blind and harden is not always ſo: Remember, that Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is not from God as a ſin, but as a juſt Judgement upon ſome, for hardning their own Hearts. It is not poſſible (ſaith <note place="margin">Hoſ. 13. 9. Rom. 14. 4.</note> one) that we ſhould ſin by him, by whom we repent, and riſe from ſin; it is from God that we ſtand, from our ſelves that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:37874:27"/> we fall. So that God is not the Author of Sin, in giving men up to blindneſs of mind, <hi>to believe Lies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God (ſay ſome) is not angry with his own works, but he is with men for their <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>2</label> blindneſs and hardneſs; therefore he can no ways be ſaid, to harden and blind:</p>
            <p>Hardneſs and Blindneſs, as it is a ſin and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> the cauſe of Sin, ſo it is not of, nor from God, but as it is a juſt Puniſhment of ſin; ſo it is of, and from him, who (being highly provoked) is pleaſed, that the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy of the wicked ſhould be thus pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. So, that tho' this be not God's Work as it is ſin, yet it is his Work, as it is a Judgment: But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> God (ſaith others) giveth Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>3</label> to men, that their Hearts may be blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and hardened, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is true in a ſenſe; but remember <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> it is thro' the Luſts and Corruptions of mens Hearts, that they became ſuch Occaſions: Like as a rebellious Son is the more hardned by the Kindneſs and Benignity of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: The Miracles which God ſhewed in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and which Chriſt wrought before the Jews and Phariſees, and the Sermons which he, and the Apoſtles preached, had not in themſelves any Tendency to produce ſuch an Effect as this, of blindneſs: Yet theſe (you ſee) through the Luſts of their hearts, were occaſions of their hardning. The Miſtreſs of a houſe (ſays one) does not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:37874:27"/> think that ſhe is acceſſary to her ſervants Theft, becauſe ſhe ſuffereth Plate to go free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly about the Houſe, for the uſe of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; which poſſibly is a Temptation to the Luſt of her Servant, to make him, or her ſteal. God (beloved doth great things <note place="margin">Pſal. 145. 17.</note> in the world, and ſhews much Kindneſſ to the Sons of men; he gives them freely of his Mercies, and ſends his word unto them, <note place="margin">Pſal. 105. 25.</note> which to many thro' their Corruption, is an Occaſion of their hardning: The <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians</hi> hated Gods people, becauſe he bleſſed them; and in this ſenſe it is ſaid, That God <hi>turned their Hearts to hate his people, to deal ſubtilly with his Servants:</hi> God (ſays <hi>David) turned their Hearts to hate his people,</hi> &amp;c. That is, by the Occaſion of thoſe Benefits which he beſtowed upon them: Thus many are blinded, by the Preaching <note place="margin">Let ſuch conſider this Text well. Luk. 29. 19, 20.</note> of the word, they thro' their Corruptions, pervert it to their own Diſtruction. As the middle region of the Air, (ſays one) is more cold by the <hi>Antiporiſtaſis;</hi> ſo, the hearts of many are more hardned, not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly but accidentally, by the preaching of the Goſpel. Now, will you call theſe Occaſions, <hi>viz.</hi> God ſhewing of mercy, and giving his holy word? Is he unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in this? Surely, no: Are not they <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 1. 2.</note> wicked indeed, who ſin <hi>becauſe Grace abounds.</hi> How many Peoples Eyes are evil, becauſe Gods are good; they are ſinſul, becauſe he is merciful and long ſuffering. <hi>Solomon</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:37874:28"/> telleth us of ſome, who are ſo vile, that becauſe Sentence <hi>againſt an evil work, is not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ecc. 8. 11. Rom: 2. 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>executed ſpeedily, therefore their hearts are ſet in them fully to do evil.</hi> There be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who becauſe God takes them not at their word, and damn them in the Act of ſin, that are the more vile, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume upon that mercy <hi>and Goodneſs that ſhould lead them to true Repentance:</hi> But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly.</hi> God (ſaith ſome) knew, that theſe <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>4</label> Sinners would take Occaſions, by the means he gave them, to grow worſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This muſt be granted, for God knows all things that have been, are, and ſhall be <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> in the world: For he is an omniſcient God, and there is nothing that is, or can be hid from his all-ſeeing Eye. But what if God did know this, muſt he therefore be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with Injuſtice, in giving the means of Grace? Surely, no. Suppoſe beloved, any of you knew, that your Counſels, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections or Inſtructions, given to your Children, would make them the worſe; Muſt you not therefore uſe theſe Medinms, which are indeed good Methods to make them better: I think I need ſay no more, to ſhew and evince to you, that it is neither contrary to the pure Juſtice and Kindneſs of God to puniſh Sin with Sin, giving up ſtubborn and rebellious Sinners to vile Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and a reprobate mind. Therefore</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I ſhall wind up all by way of <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Application. </seg>4</label> Application.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:37874:28"/>
            <p>By way of Information, in theſe three <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>1</label> things.</p>
            <p>You may ſee here, that as an ill Stomach <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ </seg>1</label> turns good meat into bad Humours, ſo good things prove hurtful to wicked men, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to the Contemners of the Goſpel. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> telleth us, <hi>That riches are kept for the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 5. 13.</note> 
               <hi>owners thereof, for their hurt;</hi> make ſome men rich, and then they will be proud, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, and profane. If <hi>Saul</hi> be a King, he will run from God to the Devil; if <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. it. 21, 22, 23, 24. Conſider this Text well.</note> be an Apoſtle, it will be a Snare to him. Oh! How doth Sin turn our Mercies into Judgement, and makes thoſe things which are Bleſſings, to be Curſes to us, and prove means to our greater Condemnation. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> See here, what cauſe you have that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">infer. </seg>2</label> to admire diſcriminating Grace. Why are you taken, and others left? You enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and others blinded; is not this free di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 7. 8. Matt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 11, 12.</note> Grace? who ſays <hi>Paul, hath made thee to differ? Or what haſt thou, that thou haſt not received? Why doſt thou boaſt, as if thou hadſt not received?</hi> Oh! Admire the free Grace of God, in Chriſt; for to you it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to know the myſteries of the Kingdom of God, but to others it is hid. Bleſſed are your Eyes, for they ſee, and your Ears, for they Hear; for many <hi>Prophets,</hi> and Righteous Men have deſired to hear thoſe things which you heard, and to ſee thoſe things which you have ſeen, and have not ſeen them. Oh won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Grace! You may, and ought all that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:37874:29"/> believe, to ſay with <hi>Paul</hi> who was a great admirer of free Grace: <hi>By the Grace of God,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 10.</note> 
               <hi>I am what I am;</hi> by the Grace of God, I am out of Hell; by the Grace of God, I that was a Perſecutor, am now a Preacher of Chriſt, and his Goſpel. I that was a Child of Wrath, and an Heir of Hell, am now an Heir of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; I that was a Rebel, am now made a Saint; I that was in the gall of bitterneſs, and in the Devils Kingdom, am now by rich Grace tranſlated into the Kingdom of Chriſt. Thus may you all ſay, who thro' Grace have believed, and do believe in Chriſt: For 'tis by Grace (from firſt to laſt) <hi>that you</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 5. 8.</note> 
               <hi>are Saved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, <hi>3dly,</hi> ſee here, and Learn, that you <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Infer. </seg>3</label> ought to juſtify God in all his diſpenſations in the World. Thus did holy <hi>David,</hi> when God had deſerted, and afflicted him, and ſeemed not to harken to the voice of his roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Thou art O Lord (ſaith he) holy thou that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 22. 1, 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Inhabiteſt the praiſes of Iſrael.</hi> God, I have told you is not unjuſt in any thing that he doth. <hi>Who art thou O Man, that replieſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 20.</note> 
               <hi>God? Shall the thing formed, ſay to him that formed it, why haſt thou made me thus?</hi> Shall the Wood quarrel with the Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? The Iron with the Smith? Shall ſorry ſinful man quarrel with <hi>God? Woe unto him that ſtriveth with his Maker. Let the Potſherd</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 45. 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrive with the Potſherds of the Earth.</hi> Oh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence the ſecrets of <hi>God,</hi> and do not quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with him! Inquire not into the reaſon of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37874:29"/> his doings which thou canſt not underſtand; if you could underſtand it, you would under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand much more, that you have no juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to complain againſt <hi>God:</hi> Oh, be ſure that you acknowledge that to be Juſt which the holy <hi>God</hi> doth! <hi>There be many things,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 29. 39.</note> 
               <hi>which the Wiſe God hath not revealed:</hi> Oh do not ſearch them, nor cenſure them; for he is Juſt in all! <hi>God</hi> ſuffered the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> about 2000 Years (ſaith one) to walk in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and then he revealed the Goſpel to them. What is the reaſon? Is there more merit in us than in our fore Fathers? Surely no, our Impiety is a like: Who can under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the reaſon? Wee ſee the thing, but <note place="margin">Pſal. 39. 9. Jer. 12. 1, 2.</note> we underſtand not the cauſe. O! be dumb with <hi>David under the rod of God,</hi> and ſay with <hi>Jeremiah, the Lord is Righteous in all his wayes.</hi> Corrupt man is not to diſpute with the Holy and Juſt <hi>God</hi> about his Judgments; <note place="margin">Job 9 1. 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>he is Wiſe in Heart, and Mighty in Strength who hath hardned himſelf againſt him, and hath proſpered:</hi> Thus much for Information: The,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2d.</hi> Uſe is by way of examination: What good O Chriſtians have you received by the <note place="margin">2. Uſe of Tryal. 2 Cor. 2. 15. 16. Rom. 2. 16, 17. Mie. 2. 12.</note> Word? Have you ſound it to be <hi>a ſaviour of Life unto Life, and the power of God to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of your Souls? Doth not my word</hi> ſaith <hi>God, do good to the upright:</hi> O examine what good you have found by the <hi>Goſpel?</hi> You have been hearers of it many Years; what! Have you received no Soul-benefit by it? Let me ask you two, or three queſtions, and do you ask them ſeriouſly your own Souls.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:37874:30"/>
            <p>Have you been ſavingly enlightned by the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt </seg>1</label> Spirit in the Word? Can you ſay with the blind man, upon good grounds, I was born blind, but now I ſee? Are your Eyes beloved, opened, and Illuminated to ſee the evil of ſin, and the good that is in Jeſus Chriſt? Every <note place="margin">Eph. i. 18. 19.</note> one that is brought to Chriſt, &amp; Intereſted in him, are Spiritually Illuminated; their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, which were darkned, are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned by the Spirit: Is it thus with you? Have the Spirit by the Word, ſet up a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Light in your Souls? <hi>Is the Veil taken</hi> from off your Eyes? Are you that <hi>were dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 16. Eph. 5. 8. Acts 26. 18 1 Cor 4. 5, 6.</note> in the abſtract, <hi>made Light in the Lord? Are you turned from Darkneſs to Light, and from the power of Satan, to God.</hi> In a Word, Hath <hi>God commanded the Light to ſhine into your Souls,</hi> and ſhewn you his Glory, <hi>in the face of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> God (ſaith <hi>Paul)</hi> that commandeth the Light to ſhine out of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, hath ſhined into our hearts: to give the Light of the Knowledg, of the glory of <hi>God</hi> in the face of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> Is it thus with you? Have you found <hi>God</hi> dealing thus with your Souls?</p>
            <p>Are your hard and frozen Hearts, ſoftned <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt, </seg>2</label> by the Word? Have any of you in good earneſt, been made to cry out with them 3000 that were pricked at the Heart, under <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon? Men and Brethren, what ſhall we do? That beloved, which neither can be bruiſed, nor broken with any ſtrokes, nor ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with any Moiſture, is hard indeed: By
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37874:30"/> this you may know your Hearts: Will no means, and monitions of the Word, break your Hearts? Will no exhortations, entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, nor promiſes in it melt you? Surely thy heart, O ſinner! Muſt be hardned indeed, that nothing will move, nor melt it. Oh! have the Word, or rather the Spirit by the Word, broken, and melted any of your Hearts? Have you found it a hammer, and a fire? <hi>A hammer to break</hi> your rocky Hearts, <note place="margin">Jer. 23. 29.</note> and a fire, to burn up your Luſts, and melt down your hearts into Godly Sorrow. Can you mourn for ſin, as ſin? And are you grieved that you can love Chriſt no better, nor bring forth no more Fruit for his Glory? are you concerned for his abſence? And do you greatly rejoyce in his preſence? If it be thus, 'tis a good ſign your hearts are ſoftned.</p>
            <p>Are you transformed by the Goſpel, into the Image of Chriſt? <hi>Is the Old man put off,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>3</label> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 22, 23.</note> with is deeds, and the New man put on? Can you truly ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi> from good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, <hi>we all with open face, beholding as in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor 3. 18.</note> 
               <hi>a glaſs, the Glory of the Lord,</hi> are changed into the ſame Image, from Glory to Glory? Even by the Spirit of our <hi>God,</hi> have you had tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming ſights of Chriſt, in the pure Glaſs of the Goſpel: Are you become new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? Can you remember, it was not with you once, as it is now? Is ſin Loth ſome, and Chriſt Lovely to you? Then you have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved good by the Word; and it is not a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but a Mercy to you.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:37874:31"/>
            <p>
               <hi>3d.</hi> Uſe is by way of exhortation. Oh! <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>3</label> Let me exhort you all in the Name, and Fear of the dreadful God, to theſe few following things, and I ſhall ſoon have done.</p>
            <p>Firſt, be exhorted and perſwaded to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> from all ſin, but eſpecially from ſins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Light, and Knowledg. A good Man thro' the violence of temptation, or Infirmity, may ſin againſt knowledge, as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> did: But have a care (as one ſays) of cold blood, and continuing in known ſins: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that knowledg taketh away all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe of ſin. <hi>If I had not come</hi> (ſays Chriſt to the <hi>Jews) and ſpoken to them, they had not had</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 12. 22.</note> 
               <hi>ſin;</hi> but now they have no Cloak, or Excuſe for their ſin: Ignorance (if not affected) may excuſe a <hi>tanto,</hi> but not a <hi>toto;</hi> but Knowledg will not excuſe any. Doſt thou know that drunkenneſs O Man! is a ſin? And that Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Whoredom, and Sabboth-breaking, are abominable ſins; and yet Live in them? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! what hope canſt thou have? A willing practiſe of known ſins, and true repentance, cannot ſtand together: Nay remember it, 'tis the ready way to a reprobate Mind, and to Eternal Ruine: Tho' (while in this mortal State) you cannot but ſin; yet beware of two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, of being willingly Ignorant of that, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> God gives you the means to know: This O ſinner! Is the mark of a Reprobate Wretch. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us of ſome that are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly Ignorant of this; <hi>that by the Word of</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:37874:31"/> 
               <hi>the Lord, the Heavens were of Old.</hi> There <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 5, 6.</note> be many that do not know Chriſt ſavingly; and this is their miſery; they do not deſire to know him: They ſay unto God, <hi>depart from</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job. 21. 4.</note> 
               <hi>us, we deſire not the Knowledg of thy ways:</hi> Oh! beware of this, for to be Ignorant, and not deſire to know, is a ſad ſign of a hardned Heart, and a blinded Mind.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>2dly.</hi> beware of doing contrary to your knowledg; <hi>For to him that knoweth to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. James 4. 18</note> 
               <hi>do good, and doth it not, to him it is a ſin.</hi> His knowledg aggravates his fault. To ſin againſt Light, and Knowledg, is a crimſon ſin; a ſin, of a deep dye. Every infirmity, every thing that falls ſhort of the Rule, is ſin; but much more, that which contradicts the Rule. This Man's ſin is a hainous ſin, a capital ſin; 'tis a ſin with a witneſs, and will be puniſhed with a vengance: If he that ſins Ignorantly, will be damned, ſurely then, he that doth not what he knows, but contrary, ſhall be double <note place="margin">Luk. 12. 47.</note> damned. <hi>He that knoweth his Maſter's Will, and doth it not, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, <hi>2dly,</hi> be exhorted to comply and fall in with the motions of the Bleſſed Spirit in the Word. Do not the Spirit at no time move upon your Hearts, and cauſe ſome convictions in your Conſciences? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Oh! ſee, that when the Spirit move, you do not reſiſt; <hi>For his Spirit</hi> (God hath ſaid) <hi>ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 6.</note> 
               <hi>not always ſtrive with Man.</hi> Oh! quench not the Spirit, turn not a deaf Ear to his Calls; do not drown his convictions (as ſome
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37874:32"/> in a Cup of Ale, or in merry Company. But I muſt not inlarge: Therefore in the</p>
            <p>Third and laſt Place; Be exhorted and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> perſwaded dayly to fear and dread, being hardned by the Goſpel; a hardned Heart is a moſt heavy Judgement; the more it is upon a man, the leſs he feels it; and the further he is from a poſſibility of repenting truly, and believing in Chriſt for Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; he muſt needs run head-long to evil, and to Hell, whom the Devil drives. But,</p>
            <p>Some may ask me, what they muſt do <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> to eſcape this Judgement, of being blinded and hardned by the Word. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, When ever you hear the Word preached, hear it with Reverence and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, <hi>Keep thy Foot when thou goeſt to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccles. 5. 1, 2. Pſal. 119. 11.</note> 
               <hi>the houſe of God, be reverent in his Preſence, and hear the word with due Attention,</hi> as it is the word of God: Let it not go in at one Ear, and out of the other, but hide it in your hearts, that you may not ſin againſt God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Meditate upon the Grace of God in Chriſt, to poor ſinners; think dayly on the freeneſs, fulneſs and riches of it: If the ſerious Thoughts of Grace and Love to undone Sinners, will not melt you, and conſtrain you to leave your ſins and love Chriſt, who have loved you to the Death; I know not what will: The prodigal Son when he thought of the fulneſs of Bread, that was in his Fathers Houſe; then he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:37874:32"/> to return home, and fell down at his Fathers Feet, and ſaid, <hi>Father, I have ſinned</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 15. 18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>againſt Heaven, and before thee, and am not worthy to be called thy Son.</hi> Nothing like Grace and Love to conſtrain, melt, and humble the Sinner. Oh! Think much on God's Love and Grace.</p>
            <p>But laſtly, For I muſt not enlarge; pray <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> earneſtly to God for a ſoft and tender heart; plead his Covenant Promiſe; who hath ſaid, <hi>That he will take away the Heart of Stone, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezek: 36. 26.</note> 
               <hi>give a heart of Fleſh:</hi> Oh! Pray that every Sermon may ſoften your Heart, <hi>and melt it</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 2.</note> 
               <hi>down into godly Sorrow:</hi> Many cry God damn me, but there's few in good earneſt; <hi>Pray for Grace, and for a tender Heart:</hi> Oh! <note place="margin">1. Thes. 5. 17. Luk. 18. 1. 6.</note> Turn the word preached into Prayer; and ſay, <hi>Lord, make this and every word of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a good word unto my Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall add do more, but leave what hath been ſaid to the Bleſſing of the GREAT GOD.</p>
            <closer>SOLIDEO GLORIA.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:37874:33"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pray, Courteous Reader, mend with your Pen theſe following Faults.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PAge 7. line 32. <hi>for</hi> Sword <hi>read</hi> Fear. In the ſame Page, <hi>for</hi> Temption <hi>read</hi> Temptation. Page 13. line 23. <hi>for</hi> Means <hi>read</hi> Meant. Page 9. line 3. <hi>for</hi> Judiciouſly <hi>read</hi> Judicially. Page 15. line 32. <hi>for</hi> Promulging <hi>read</hi> Promulgation. Page 38. line 3. <hi>for</hi> Ways <hi>read</hi> Voice. Page 39. line 10. <hi>for</hi> Pleaſures <hi>read</hi> Pleaſure. In the ſame, <hi>for</hi> To <hi>read</hi> Into.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37874:33"/>
            <head>A FUNERAL SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> iv. Verſe vii. viii.</bibl>
               <q>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my courſe, I have kept the Faith: Henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Lord the Righteous Judge ſhall give me at that Day: And not to me only, but unto all them alſo that love his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>SOlomon</hi> the Wiſe tells us; <hi>To every thing there is a Seaſon, and a Time, a Time to be Born, and a Time to Die, a Time to Mourn, and a Time to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce,</hi> Eccleſ. 3. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I doubt not, All the Godly and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and Senſible here preſent, will readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37874:34"/> acknowledge with me, That this is a <hi>Time to Mourn:</hi> But will it not look like the adventuring on a <hi>Paradox,</hi> to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm to you, That it is alſo a <hi>Time to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Time</hi> it is indeed to <hi>Mourn</hi> for the loſs of ſo dear a Relation, and ſo Pious and Chriſtian a Friend: But are we not Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians as well as Men? And while Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſeeles, ſighs, nay ſinks at the diſmal Loſs of Friends, or Relations; Grace ſhould triumph over Nature, and Faith over Senſe. While we are bemoaning their loſs, we ſhould be Rejoycing in the Crown and Glory of Saints, of which number ſhe was we have ſo great Reaſon to be aſſured. Our Deceaſed Friend was one of their Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, who by their Holy Converſation give a plain, and ſenſible demonſtration of the Power of the Principles of our Holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, both by their Life, and their Death; For Words have not that <hi>Energy</hi> and <hi>Force,</hi> that Action and Converſation hath; a ſhining Life, and a triumphant Death, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade beyond all the Power of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or charms of Rethoric.</p>
            <p>And concerning the not only unblamea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs, but Piouſneſs of her Life, for whoſe Death we now Mourn, it was ſo well known to all that knew her, that ſhe hath therein a better Character, than I can give her; for modeſty of Stile, and Reſerves of Expreſſion become me, when I conſider the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37874:34"/> Modeſty and Humility of her Deportment, through the whole of her Life.</p>
            <p>I come therefore now to the Text I have propoſed to Diſcourſe upon. The whole Text is drawn in Figures, borow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the <hi>Olimpic Games,</hi> well known in the Times, and Places in which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle wrote. <hi>Games</hi> appointed for all the activities of Perſons, prepared by Frame, and Conſtitution of Body, Vigour of Mind, and Inclination, and ſtrictly Diſciplined, Dieted, and Exerciſed thereunto: Such an alluſion is at other times made uſe of by the Apoſtle, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 24. And being Sanctified by the Divine Spirit, is moſt elegant and expreſſive of holy Senſes.</p>
            <p>In this Place <hi>The Apoſtle of the Gentiles</hi> gives us under theſe <hi>Emblems</hi> a threefold Character of himſelf; and then ſets out the Prize.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His Encountring, and Combating all the Temptations of Satan within, and of the World without; wherein he <hi>Fought, not as one that beateth the Air,</hi> but at ſharps (as they ſay) with great effect for Offence and Defence, as thoſe Combatants alluded to uſed to do.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He (who received the Prize) <hi>Finiſhed his Courſe.</hi> Therein he alludes to thoſe, who <hi>Run in a Race that they might Obtain: He Ran not as in certainly:</hi> He Ran the whole <hi>Courſe</hi> of Doing and Suffering, and of his Miniſtry, and Apoſtleſhip, the whole
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37874:35"/> 
               <hi>Race ſet before him</hi> to the very <hi>Mark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>He kept the Faith,</hi> the great Faith of the Goſpel, in union to the Crucified <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> which was the ſcandal of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> even the Croſs of Chriſt, and the <hi>Obedience</hi> of Faith in all the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, <hi>Mortification</hi> to the <hi>World,</hi> and the Luſts of it within, and without; and doth extend to all kinds of Suffering, Heavenly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Mind, and Converſation: Hereby he behaved himſelf, as a mighty <hi>Champion,</hi> that by no means would let go his Hold, or <hi>Depoſium,</hi> the <hi>Pearl</hi> of <hi>great Prize,</hi> or ſurrender it to the violence againſt it.</p>
            <p>And ſo he leads us to the ſecond Part of this great Text, under the ſame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion, The <hi>Crown,</hi> or the <hi>Prize;</hi> not the <hi>Corruptible Crown</hi> of thoſe Games, but the <hi>Incorruptible;</hi> to which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle refers, <hi>a Man is not Crowned</hi> except he <hi>ſtrive Lawfully;</hi> and herein he thus expreſſes himſelf; <hi>Henceforth is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Righteous Lord ſhall give me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I begin with the Firſt Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, I would conſider the Apoſtles Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of himſelf; <hi>I have Fought, I have Finiſhed, I have Kept.</hi> Now it is certain the Apoſtle, who acknowledges himſelf <hi>chief of Snners,</hi> and <hi>leaſt of Saints,</hi> would not ſpeak of himſelf, as in, or of, or by himſelf; but is to be interpreted by 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 10. &amp;c. <hi>By the Grace of God I am what</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37874:35"/> 
               <hi>I am; and not I, but the Grace of God that was with me.</hi> And <hi>Gal. 2. 10. I Live, yet not I; but Chriſt Liveth in me.</hi> Altho' therefore at the firſt view, the Apoſtle may appear, as a ſelf-Subſiſting, a ſelf-Confident Perſon in that three fold (I:) Yet when we duly weigh what he ſays in thoſe places, <hi>Not I:</hi> It ſhews, when he ſpeaks thus, he conſiders himſelf as in Chriſt the <hi>Head,</hi> and <hi>Saviour of the Body,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented his, in all he Did and Suffered. But further, He is in all his united to him by Faith, He <hi>doth all their Works in them, and for them,</hi> and thus in him, by the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er they receive from him, by being <hi>ſtrong in the Grace, that is, in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> They do all, They do, ſo that the Apoſtle when he ſaith, (I) does not mean himſelf, by (I) as ſingle, ſolitary, divided from Chriſt; but as in him, by him; as to the Strength, Life, Principle he acted from. He did all in Chriſt; and not only ſo, but as the Power, and the Action flowing from it was in Chriſt; So the acceptance, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up the Imperfections, the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Guilt, the Corruption; <hi>The ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him free from the Law of Sin and Death;</hi> In regard of condemnation falling upon Sin <hi>dwelling</hi> in <hi>him.</hi> In all this, he looks wholly to Chriſt; and ſo his <hi>Figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Finiſhing his Courſe, keeping the Faith,</hi> Are to be limited; <hi>Not I,</hi> but Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone did all in me and was accepted for me</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:37874:36"/>
            <p>This is therefore, the not only Encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement, but the very ſupport, nay more, the ſubſiſtnce of Saints in all their holy Action and Motion: All is in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And this is their conſolation in the midſt of ſo many Clouds of Guilt, and Imperfection; that they <hi>have a faithful and merciful high Prieſt who makes Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation;</hi> and perfumes their Perſons, and ſervices with his much <hi>Incenſe.</hi> And tho' many are ignorant of this great Goſpel Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, this was the conſolation of our Friend in her Dying Hours.</p>
            <p>Now this Explication of the Apoſtles as it ſhuts out on one ſide all the Phariſaie Boaſts in our ſelves, all the Self-righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Self-ſufficiency of Legaliſts; ſo it ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly condemns all the Licentious pretenſions of Carnaliſts, to live as they pleaſe; or to be Slothful, Negligent, Careleſs, Unactive in theſe great Tranſactions: For though they live all in Chriſt, depend wholly on Him for acceptance; yet all His are under the Holy <hi>Conſtraints</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> and the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of Filial Obedience; and Chriſt in them is a Principle of Spiritual Life, and Higheſt Activity. So that they can neither be looſe or plead <hi>Liberty</hi> as a <hi>Cloak of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs,</hi> nor be dull, and ſtupid in the ways of Chriſt. And herein our Deceaſed Friend had learned Chriſt; In all things ſenſible of Duty; but Living as to Juſtification and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with God above. With thoſe, who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37874:36"/> are the <hi>Circumciſion, Worſhipping God in the Spirit, rejoicing in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> and having <hi>no confidence in the Fleſh,</hi> and ſo ſhe was able, though ſo young a Perſon, to ſing the Song of Victory: <hi>O Death Where is thy Sting? Oh Grave! Where is thy Victory? I thank God through Jeſus Chriſt my Lord, who hath given me the Victory.</hi> This made Her ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire a remove out of the Body, <hi>and to be with Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have given the True Evangelical ſenſe of the Apoſtle placing ſo much upon himſelf, <hi>I have Fought,</hi> and <hi>Finiſhed,</hi> and <hi>Kept.</hi> 'Tis but as if he had ſaid, I have, <hi>I can do all things through Chriſt ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neing me:</hi> and I can look look upon all with Joy and Triumph, becauſe all my Impurities and Imperfections are anſwered for, and my Perſon is waſhed with the <hi>pure Water</hi> of his <hi>Sacrificing Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us then conſider the great ſence of the Apoſtle; <hi>I have faught a good Fight.</hi> Wherein he comes forth in the ſtrength of <hi>Jehovah Jeſus Chriſt the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> As <hi>David the Warrior of the Lord,</hi> under the <hi>Captain of Salvation.</hi> Reſolved, and arm'd at all Points; and that had with Courage and Fidelity, almoſt now to the very laſt, carried on ſo far, as his Station reach'd, the full Conqueſt and Victory of Jeſus Chriſt, he is now <hi>triumphing</hi> over all <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Explaining of this warfare, in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37874:37"/> the warrs of the Lord, as they are ſtil'd, <hi>Numb.</hi> 21. 14. We are to conſider the <hi>Great Lord mighty in Battle,</hi> who arms all his; even the Lord Jeſus, who appoints them; who are therefore ſtiled <hi>Good Soldiers of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who hath Redeemed them, from being ſlaves of Juſtice, of Wrath, of Satan; and they therefore are ſaid to <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by the Blood of the Lamb.</hi> So their very ſetting out is by his <hi>Blood;</hi> They are Arm'd by him with Courage, Spirit, and Might within. <hi>He teaches their hands to War, and their Fingers to Fight; by him they run through a Troop, by him they leape over a Wall;</hi> it is he that <hi>Girdeth them with ſtrength to the Battel, that they may help the Lord againſt, the mighty;</hi> and that all Enemies may be ſubdued to him; and trherefore the Fight is called a good Fight with great Reaſon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Apoſtle had to Fight with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, his carnal Reaſon to <hi>Throw down the ſtrong holds of that, to bring every thought into Captivity to Chriſt,</hi> all thoſe high Thoughts of ſelf-Righteouſueſs, to ſlight all <hi>conferences with Fleſh and Blood, and to repel them, when tempted to ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal Treaties; to bring under the Law of his Members that warred againſt the Law of his Mind, and would bring him into Captivity to the Law of Sin, and Death, to bring under ſubjection that carnal Mind; that is enmity to God; not ſubject to the Law</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:37874:37"/> 
               <hi>of God, nither indeed can be; that in dwelling Sin.</hi> All thoſe <hi>Willings</hi> and <hi>Luſtings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Spirit;</hi> In regard of which, the Apoſtle Expreſſes himſelf in the Langu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of a Combatant in thoſe Games, that deals the moſt ſubduing, and mortifying Strokes and Blows; ſo he upon all Bodily Inclinations and Luſts. And this is one great Point of the good Fight, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle reviews with ſo much comfort: But it is in Chriſt, and through Chriſt, by whom, in whom as <hi>Crucified with him,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh</hi> with its <hi>Luſts</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> are <hi>Crucified</hi> and not in, or by himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle had to Fight with the World, in all both its inticements and bland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhments, and in regard of its Threats, Rages, and Perſecutions; In both regards ſaith He, <hi>I am Crucified to the World, and the World to me,</hi> Gal. 6. 14. But it is in Chriſt, and his Croſs alone enabled Him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He had to Fight with all the Enemies of the Goſpel of Chriſt, in reſiſtance to the Grace of Chriſt in the Hearts of all, to whom He Preached; For ſpeaking of the Preaching of the Goſpel, He ſaith, <hi>The Weapons of our Warfare are mighty:</hi> So with the open profeſſed Oppoſitions to the Truth of Chriſt in his Redemption. To the <hi>Jews</hi> a <hi>Scandal;</hi> as it it was contrary to all the Revelation of God, in the <hi>Old Teſtament;</hi> and to the <hi>Gentiles Fooliſhneſs</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:37874:38"/> as if it had no Agreement with the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Learning, and Wit of Men of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and Accompliſhment, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 23.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He had to Fight with the <hi>Powers of Darkneſs, Spiritual Wickedneſſes in high Places;</hi> as every Chriſtian hath, For as He ſays, <hi>we War not;</hi> That is, not principally; <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Fleſh, and Blood, but againſt Principalities and Powers, the Rulers of the Darkneſs of this World.</hi> And for the maintaining this Fight, He had the ſame neceſſity with all Saints; <hi>To take to himſelf the whole Armor of God, that he might ſtand in the evil day, and having drne all to ſtand,</hi> Eph. 6. 10.</p>
            <p n="5">5. All the Perſecutors, and their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, like the <hi>Beaſts of Epheſus,</hi> in what Senſe ſoever taken, He had to Fight with; wherein He ſuffered, <hi>as an evil doer;</hi> and was <hi>Killed all the Day long.</hi> But in all, <hi>He was more than a conqueror, through him who Loved him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. He had to Fight with Guilt, Death and the Grave, the <hi>Wrath to come;</hi> and with all the unbelief of his own Heart; But he <hi>over came</hi> by the continual Application He made to the Death and Reſurrection of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who <hi>Loved him, and gave himſelf for him, in whom he deſired to be Found.</hi> So that he Ran up to that aſſurance, to make that challenge, <hi>who ſhall lay any thing to my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>harge, as one of Gods Elect;</hi> to be aſſured, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat neither <hi>Life, nor Death, Things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37874:38"/> nor Things to come, ſhould be able to ſeparate him from the Love of Chriſt;</hi> and ſo he could Sing that Triumphant Song; <hi>Oh Death where is thy Sting? Oh Grave where is thy Victory? The Sting of Death is Sin; the Strength of Sin is the Law, but thanks be to God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> as in the caſe of the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Death.</hi> All he places ſtill in Chriſt; and thus we ſee on all accounts, <hi>The Apoſtle Fought a good Fight,</hi> and through Chriſt had the Proſpect of a High and Noble End of the VVar, that is, of Victory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Head</hi> 2. I come then to the Second Point of the Apoſtles Triumphing Declaration of his own State in Chriſt; <hi>I have finiſhed my courſe;</hi> That we may rightly apprehend, Here are two things to be underſtood by it.</p>
            <p>I. The General courſe of a Chriſtian State in its own Motion, Action, Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from the Time of Converſion unto the very Hour of Death. This was one thing the Apoſtle underſtood by his courſe, for God having drawn out the Line of Life, as he hath ſeen fit for every one of his Servants; Their courſe of Chriſtian Action is by him drawn out proportionable; So that there is no part to be unadorn'd; Something of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, Private, Secret, Unholy Action is to be applyed to every part of it; There muſt be a <hi>Running</hi> to <hi>obtain:</hi> It is called therefore <hi>Running the Race, that is ſet before us; Looking to Jeſus;</hi> to ſhew in whoſe ſtrength
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37874:39"/> the whole Race is run; So, It is expreſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>David,</hi> by his <hi>ſerving his Generation according to the will of God;</hi> and of <hi>Johns ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling his courſe,</hi> as a Servant of God in a Holy Converſation, beſides his Miniſterial ſervice: How many great concernments hath every Chriſtian to look to; His Implantation into Chriſt, Renovation, <hi>New Creation;</hi> The <hi>In-dwelling</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the Graces, and Fruits of it; His <hi>Living, walking in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; The work of Faith with Power; Sorrow after God working Repentance to Salvation never to be Repented of. The conſtraining Love of Chriſt, the living to him, the dying Dayly;</hi> Converſe with the <hi>Word of God, Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Reading, Meditation,</hi> Holy Diſcourſe, Prayer, Thankſgiving; Self-denyal, Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, being <hi>made meet to be Partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light:</hi> All theſe with much more ſet before us in Scripture, ſhew us, what the <hi>Race</hi> of a Chriſtian is; what his <hi>courſe</hi> is; Now to find our Heart engag'd herein, with all earneſtneſs <hi>Preſſing forward to reach the mark</hi> by the utmoſt ſtretch and extending our ſelves to it, is what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks of himſelf: He had run on in this Chriſtian courſe, on this Line, to very near the End of his Line of Life; and it is a Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Review of a ſincere, much more of an Eminent Chriſtian; while he can behold Chriſt, the <hi>Alpha,</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the Beginning, and End of All; All the Haltings, the Falls, Falſe-ſteps, the many Lingerings, made up,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37874:39"/> Anſwered, and Attoned for by the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and Finiſher of our Faith, who for the Joy ſett before Him,</hi> ran the whole courſe, the Father Lin'd out to Him, <hi>Doing always the things pleaſing in his ſight;</hi> Who ſet every ſtep according to his Obediential Love to the Father, and thefore went forth to his Death with higheſt Reſolution; <hi>Let us Ariſe</hi> (ſaith he) and <hi>(John 14. 31.) Go hence: He endured the Croſs, deſpiſed the ſhame, and is ſet down on the right hand of the Majeſty on High:</hi> And thus his ſervants <hi>follow his ſteps,</hi> and ſo we have reaſon to hope of this his Servant, that ſhe was ſwift, ſhe <hi>Finiſhed her courſe,</hi> ſhe Finiſhed the courſe ſhe was ſett in, though a more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, and retired one, before ſhe was <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited,</hi> as the true ſenſe of that word, we Tranſlate <hi>(Not ſuffered)</hi> ſignifies, <hi>Heb. 7. 21. To continue any longer therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. There is yet a higher, and more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted ſenſe of the Apoſtle <hi>Finiſhing his courſe;</hi> not a more ſubſtantial or Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental ſenſe; For that is indeed the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental; All the redeemed of Chriſt in, and by him, running their courſe, and ſo entring into their <hi>Maſters Joy;</hi> but there was alſo in all times a more Publick, and high ſphere of Action; Into which God hath been pleaſed to raiſe ſome of his ſervants; and there hath not been a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, then the Miniſtry of the Goſpel; and moſt particularly, the Apoſtolick; and to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37874:40"/> this undoubtedly the Apoſtle had regard, when he here ſaith, <hi>I have Finiſhed my courſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For herein the Apoſtle had a Line given to him and a <hi>meaſure,</hi> the <hi>meaſure of the Line,</hi> which he would not <hi>ſtretch himſelf, nor into other Mens Labours,</hi> but according the Rule or Line preſcribed him by God, 2 <hi>Cor. 10. 13, &amp;c.</hi> And this was ſo abundant, that he <hi>Laboured more abundanily,</hi> then <hi>any other,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 10. <hi>He was the Apoſtle of the Gentiles, Miniſtring the Goſpel of God</hi> ſo to them, that the <hi>offering up of the Gentiles</hi> might be a <hi>Sacrifice, Acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> being <hi>ſanctified by the Holy Spirit;</hi> which was indeed a high ſphere of Chriſtian Goſpel-Activity; and whereof he ſaith, <hi>He might Glory;</hi> And <hi>the Line was ſo every way enlarged,</hi> that he <hi>Preached</hi> the <hi>Goſpel</hi> round <hi>about from Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem to Illyricum,</hi> Rom. 15. 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He did fully, or <hi>Fulfil to Preach the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>He ſtrived to Preach where Chriſt had not been Named;</hi> And all this was made efficacious, by <hi>Mighty Signs,</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> by the <hi>Power of the Spirit of God.</hi> So that it was beſt for the Churches, and more needful he ſhould <hi>continue, though to his loſs,</hi> Phil. 1. 21. In all this Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; He was moſt mindful to aſcribe all to <hi>Grace,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 10. <hi>By the Grace of God be was All,</hi> that <hi>He was;</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:37874:40"/> and after all his Diſcourſe of <hi>his Line,</hi> and <hi>meaſure,</hi> He concludes; <hi>He that Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, Let him Glory in the Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. 10. 17. The Apoſtle <hi>Finiſhed this courſe,</hi> under and by the <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtle</hi> of <hi>our Profeſſion,</hi> whoſe the fupreme Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in all is; Inaſmuch as <hi>He,</hi> who <hi>Built the Houſe hath more Honour,</hi> then the <hi>Houſe;</hi> whoſe <hi>Houſe</hi> with all <hi>Prophets, Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> Heb. 3. 1. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle was; For He, who <hi>Built All Things</hi> in his Church, is <hi>God</hi> and <hi>our Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Head</hi> 3. I come now to the third Head, or Character, the Apoſtle gives of himſelf. <hi>I have kept the Faith:</hi> This Completes the whole: Herein the Apoſtle ſpeaks again, as a mighty Champion, that retain'd the Riches of Faith, <hi>Much more precious, then of</hi> Gold, <hi>that Periſheth:</hi> The Faith he retain'd with ſuch a Might, and would by no means ſuffer it to be forced out of his Hand.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Great Principal, and moſt eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Faith, the Apoſtle kept, or held faſt, is Jeſus Chriſt Himſelf, and his Righteouſneſs, who is pleaſed, becauſe he himſelf is indeed the All of Faith, to be ſtyled <hi>Faith</hi> it ſelf, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is the whole Truth of the Goſpel, as the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> gives it the Honourable Title of the <hi>Faith once, at once,</hi> once for All; <hi>Delivered to the Saints,</hi> Jude 3. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37874:41"/> the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Faith</hi> by which the <hi>Juſt Live,</hi> and receive even full aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of underſtanding: <hi>The Righteouſneſs of God revealed from Faith to Faith;</hi> The <hi>Faith</hi> embracing the <hi>truth that is after Godlineſs,</hi> which whoever walks contrary to, <hi>denies the Faith;</hi> The Faith that looks to the Eternal State and Condition; which <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> denying by ſaying, <hi>The Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was paſt already, overthrew the Faith of ſome.</hi> This the Apoſtle held, faſt in all the ſenſes of it, now given, and would by no means part with, or betray to any Seducers, or Adverſaries of one ſort, or other; as was before aſſerted under the firſt Character of <hi>Fighting a good Fight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The inward Grace of Faith in the Heart, and Holy confeſſion of which the Apoſtle ſaith. <hi>Rom. 10. With the Heart, Man believes unto Righteouſneſs, and with the Mouth confeſſion is made to ſalvation; The Life, he liv'd by the Faith of the Son of God,</hi> who loved him and gave himſelf for him. The Faith even the <hi>Plerophory</hi> of it, <hi>ſprinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Heart from an Evil Conſcience by the Blood of Jeſus,</hi> the Faith, by which we <hi>have Peace with God,</hi> the faith that <hi>embraces the Promiſes,</hi> by which we <hi>cleanſe our ſelves from all Filthineſs of Fleſh, and Spirit; the ſheild of faith,</hi> The Apoſtle Exhorts <hi>above all to take, to quench the fiery Darts of the Devil;</hi> The faith, by which the <hi>Elders ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſo Honourable a Teſtimony, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:37874:41"/> Heb. 11. In all thoſe their grat Acts; The faith that paſſes through all afflictions, temptations, and tryals, till thoſe Pillars are ſet up with this Inſcription, Rev. 13. <hi>Here is the Faith and Patience of the Saints, here are they, who</hi> keep the Commandments of God, and <hi>hold the Teſtimony of Jeſus;</hi> Laſtly the faith, the very preſence of <hi>things hoped for,</hi> raiſes to that <hi>Plerophory</hi> of <hi>hope, that enters within the Veil.</hi> All Saints with the Apoſtle who by faith have <hi>dyed,</hi> and <hi>ſlept in,</hi> and by <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and are <hi>entred</hi> into reſt with him, even as this ſervant of the Lord hath done by the ſame faith; and whom <hi>God even our Lord Jeſus</hi> will <hi>bring with</hi> him, the <hi>Living remaining</hi> Saints ſhall not <hi>Anticipate; The Lord my God will come, and all his Saints with him:</hi> But in all this faith, our whole ſubſiſtence is in, and by the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> and <hi>Finiſher of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo we are come to the ſecond part of the Text; <hi>Henceforth is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs;</hi> This is the <hi>Prize of the High Calling of God in Jeſus Chriſt; Eternal Glory, the Eternal Inheritance, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Redemption;</hi> the whole Excellency, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Bleſſedneſs of the Eternal State is <hi>the Inheritance of the Saints in Light;</hi> which is alone by Jeſus Chriſt in us, the <hi>Hope of Glory reſerved in Heaven:</hi> This the <hi>Lord</hi> as a <hi>Righteous Judge gives,</hi> and he gives as a <hi>Crown of Righteouſneſs;</hi> Becauſe Jeſus Chriſt hath purchaſed it with his own
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37874:42"/> Blood, and Obedience; And in him, it is that Saints are able to ſubſiſt in this Eternal Glory; Being <hi>made like him,</hi> by <hi>ſeeing him as he is;</hi> but moſt <hi>Glorious,</hi> herein is that State, <hi>He in the Father, the Father in Him;</hi> and Saints hereby in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and in <hi>the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> and <hi>the Love</hi> wherewith the Father Loved Him, even <hi>before the Foundation of the World</hi> is in them, becauſe <hi>He is in them,</hi> and in all this the Son Intercedes with the <hi>Father,</hi> as a <hi>Righteous Father,</hi> John 17. 24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To open this part of the Text, according to the Tenor of the preſent Diſcourſe, ſo far, as we have proceeded.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That expreſſion of the Apoſtle; <hi>Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth,</hi> or as the word in the <hi>Greek</hi> ſignifies, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>That which remaineth is, there is laid up for me,</hi> &amp;c. An expreſſion ſuitable to this is that, Heb. 4. 9. <hi>There remaineth a reſt for the People of God;</hi> This hath an Immutable certainty; If the Judgment of wicked Men be <hi>laid up in ſtore</hi> with God, and <hi>Sealed among his treaſures,</hi> Deut. 32. 34. How much more the Salvation, the Glory, and Bleſſedneſs of his Saints: It is as cerrain, and much more certain, then as in themſelves, the precedent <hi>Fighting the good Fight,</hi> &amp;c. For their aſſurance is not in themſelves; They would fail and come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, as Combatants not <hi>obtaining the Prize,</hi> If all the certainty were in themſelves; as the <hi>Angels</hi> not <hi>Elect,</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> fail'd, or fell
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37874:42"/> ſhort: But the Prize it ſelf to be given to them, who do <hi>Fight,</hi> and <hi>Run,</hi> is in the nature of the thing out of themſelves, and in God alone; and is aſſur'd by his Righteouſneſs, and Veracity, that cannot fail. This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder is ſo Connexed, as not poſſible to be ſeparated, from what went before; and more Impoſſible by far to fail, then what went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as in us, but as all is ſure in the Great <hi>ſurety,</hi> It is to be fulfilled in all his; Even as the Debt He paid for them is ſet far above all doubts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In this aſſurance of the <hi>Prize,</hi> the Apoſtle ſpeaks ſo triumphingly of, he ſays, <hi>The Lord, the Righteous Judge ſhall give me;</hi> He Styles the Lord, <hi>the Judge,</hi> and <hi>the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judge,</hi> in agreement with the cuſtom of thoſe Games; In which there was a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſolemnly conſtituted, who ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge the Prizes, and Determine the <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the ſtriving,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſays, a Man is not Crowned, <hi>except he ſtrive Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</hi> And it was expected from ſuch a Perſon in that State of Honour, that he ſhould be Fair, Equal, and Juſt in all his Judgment, and Determination; and it aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures the Judgment of the Lord to be in all things, admirable for its greateſt Equity, Righteouſneſs, and Judgment; <hi>For the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Lord Loveth Righteouſneſs,</hi> Pſal. 11. 7. And thus in alluſion to this in that ſo known Seat of alluſion to theſe <hi>Games,</hi> the Apoſtle ſays; <hi>I keep under my Body,</hi> and with the Auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37874:43"/> methods, <hi>Bring it into ſubjection;</hi> Leaſt while I Preach to others; I my ſelf ſhould become one <hi>Rejected,</hi> to whom the Prize is not Judg'd; one unworthy the Prize; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he who Determines, is a <hi>Righteous Judge,</hi> and will not be Impoſed upon with outſides, or Formalities.</p>
            <p>But here the great doubt is, where is the Saint to be found, who can ſtand before a Judge, <hi>a Righteous Judge, ſuch a Righteous Judge as the Lord is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the alone Anſwer is, according to what hath been ſaid already; That it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends wholly upon what hath been done by the <hi>Captain of their ſalvation;</hi> His Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and his Sacrifice, the <hi>Author,</hi> and <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher of Faith;</hi> What he hath done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them; That, in which he was wholly alone, and none of his with him; and that which he works in all his, as their <hi>Head</hi> of Life, and Influences; making them ſtrong in the <hi>Grace,</hi> that <hi>Reſides</hi> ſupremely, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally in <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and flows continually into them; and that by way of inward Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Poſſeſſion, by his <hi>Dwelling in them,</hi> John 6. 57. And they in him; <hi>Even as the Living Father ſent him, and he Lives by the Father, ſo all Believers live by Him and in Him;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This then being the Fundamental Merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Account; <hi>Chriſt All,</hi> and <hi>in All,</hi> there is a Glorious, Reſplendent Juſtice, and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Gods Adjudication of the Prize to all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37874:43"/> Saints in Him; Becauſe there is an exact Ballance, between what is Chriſts, and the Glory of the <hi>Crown,</hi> and of the <hi>Prize;</hi> So that Scripture delights in the uſe of the Word, <hi>Juſt, Righteous, Righteouſneſs</hi> in the Admenſuration to all in Chriſt <hi>at that Day Juſt,</hi> and the <hi>Juſtifier of Him that believes in Jeſus;</hi> He is <hi>Juſt to forgive us our Sins, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſueſs,</hi> by way of Acquitance, and Judiciary diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge; becauſe, <hi>The Blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son</hi> hath by <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> and Sacrifice for ſin, firſt cleanſed <hi>from all unrighteouſneſs,</hi> 1 John 1. 10. And there is an Illuſtrious <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> in the <hi>Judgment of God,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; And a Flag of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyance againſt all Adverſaries, the Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Malicious Devils, and enraged Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wicked Men, 2 <hi>Theſ. 1. 5, &amp;c.</hi> Hung out; <hi>(we tranſlate a manifeſt token) in that Day,</hi> a Day of <hi>Adjudging</hi> the Prizes; That Day of the <hi>Revelation of the Righteous Judgment of God,</hi> Rom. 2. 5.</p>
            <p>And therefore the Crown is call'd, as in ſome places a <hi>Crown of Glory,</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 4. And a <hi>Crown of Life;</hi> So here a <hi>Crown of Righteouſneſs,</hi> as due to Chriſt in his; though to us, as in our ſelves, It is a <hi>Crown give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the <hi>Gift of Free Grace;</hi> as <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to <hi>Death the wages,</hi> due demerit, deſert of Sin: It is <hi>Free Gift</hi> in Jeſus Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> upholding the Glory of Juſtice, and Rig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs in that Gift.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37874:44"/>3. The <hi>Crown</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) ſhall be given at that Day; There are two Times eminently Styled in Scripture, <hi>that Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Day of the firſt opening of the Glory of the Goſpel; and after a time of Eclipſe by the <hi>Anti-chriſtian Apoſtacy,</hi> ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out again in Glory; In which firſt and laſt the great <hi>Prophecies</hi> of Scripture are <hi>Fulfilled;</hi> we find therefore often in the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; In thoſe Days,</hi> and <hi>In that Day,</hi> as all Compriz'd under that great Point of time, the <hi>Fulneſs of time; the appearance of Chriſt in the Fleſh,</hi> Gal. 4. 4. And the time from thence running to his appearance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The, <hi>that Day</hi> of the <hi>Appearance</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, and of his <hi>Kingdom;</hi> as they are joyn'd a little before the Text; that <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of All Times,</hi> when all ſhall be placed, that is Happy and Bleſſed under their <hi>Head,</hi> Eph. 1. 10. And ſo <hi>that Day</hi> is often uſed in the Epiſtles of the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> as here, and continually; that <hi>Great Day,</hi> that <hi>Day,</hi> wherein ſhall be ſo Gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>us an Unveiling, a <hi>Revelation</hi> of the things, that have now been kept ſecret, but ſhall then be ſett out in the trueſt, and moſt Glorious Light; The Beauty of every thing in its own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſeaſon, to which God hath referr'd in that General Table of time, God hath drawn, and that <hi>Solomon</hi> gives in ſhort the Heads off, in that ſo wiſe Book, the Book of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> or of <hi>the Preacher.</hi> At the End of the ſeveral events, there recorded;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37874:44"/> ſaying, <hi>God hath made every thing Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in its ſeaſon;</hi> But, becauſe it does not, or may not without wiſe References to that Eternal World be underſtood to be ſo; He ſays, God hath ſett Eternity, or the Eternal World in their Hearts, <hi>Eccl. 3. 1, &amp;c.</hi> Then alſo are all the Great <hi>Miſteries</hi> of the Goſpel ſhall be clearly unfolded, and laid open; All the various dealings of God with his own, and with the Men of his preſent <hi>Hand,</hi> and might; the Men of <hi>this World;</hi> ſhall be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riddled, and diſengaged from all their Darks, and Intricacies, and the <hi>Crown</hi> ſett with <hi>Glory,</hi> and the <hi>Glory of Righteouſneſs</hi> on all his Saints: And this becauſe it is the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> of the <hi>Righteous Judgment of God;</hi> And then as the wicked ſhall be all in Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, <hi>Tribulation, Anguiſh,</hi> and Amazement; So Chriſt will be <hi>Glorified</hi> in the <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>Admired,</hi> in all them, who <hi>believe,</hi> who have <hi>Fought the Good Fight,</hi> ſo as <hi>not to beat the Air; They have run</hi> not as <hi>Incertainly,</hi> and as in Naval Conteſts, have not <hi>Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack'd,</hi> but held faſt the <hi>Faith:</hi> And ſo the <hi>Crown</hi> Adjudg'd to them by the <hi>Righteous Judge</hi> of the Combatants, and their Activi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in and through their great <hi>Agonothetes,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt and the ſuprme <hi>Agoniſtes,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of All, and cheif Combatant.</p>
            <p>4. The Apoſtle joyns with himſelf all thoſe, who, <hi>Love the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as thoſe, whom the <hi>Righteous Judge</hi> will <hi>give the Crown of Righteouſneſs unto,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:37874:45"/> And this expreſſion offers two conſiderations to us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That ſeeing, the Apoſtle gives this ſhort Character of Saints in General, and not ſo particularly, (as <hi>Fighting</hi> the <hi>good Fight; Finiſhing all their courſe,</hi> and <hi>keeping the Faith,)</hi> but <hi>Loving the appearance of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt;</hi> It ſhews, there may be; and there is a different eminency of Saints; But as they all meet in the <hi>Head, Root, Corner Stone;</hi> So whatever their different meaſures are in making up the <hi>full ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in Chriſt,</hi> yet they are all alike in the <hi>Glory,</hi> the <hi>Crown of Righteouſneſs;</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is all given by grace in Chriſt and ſo the Leaſt, as well as the greate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t are <hi>Crown'd</hi> in Him; He gives the ſame <hi>Crown</hi> to the Laſt, as to the Firſt, even as in the <hi>Parable,</hi> Mat. 20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In that all Saints Love the <hi>Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Chriſt,</hi> it is made certain; They are thoſe, that have <hi>Fought, Run,</hi> hell faſt the great <hi>Depoſitum, Committed to them,</hi> ſo as to obtain, and not to be rejected; the <hi>Faith,</hi> which gives them the aſſurance, and lifting up of the Head at the appearance of the great <hi>Judge,</hi> and <hi>Arbitrator</hi> of the <hi>Prize;</hi> and ſo they deſire, long for, and <hi>Love</hi> his <hi>Appearance;</hi> And thus I have given a breif View, and Examination of the words of this Great Text.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:37874:45"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Applic.</hi> That which I would now infer from the whole diſcourſe by way of Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal concluſion, by way of Practical enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by way of Conſolation, relating to the particular occaſion, ſhall be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That we would look to it; To <hi>hold the Faith</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt in its own <hi>Purity;</hi> For the Goſpel is ſo pure, ſeparate from all mixtures, as <hi>Silver Purified in a Furnace of Earth, Purified ſeven Times,</hi> that we muſt not <hi>pervert it</hi> any way; <hi>Every Word of God, Prov.</hi> 30. 5, 6. Much more the Great Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Points: Whoever add to it, or diminiſh from it, will be <hi>found Lyars unto it;</hi> Bleſſed are they that <hi>truſt in it,</hi> It will be to them a <hi>Sheild of Salvation.</hi> As to that Great Point, <hi>Righteouſneſs by Faith</hi> in Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>works;</hi> How ſuddenly do Men ſlide down to <hi>Another Goſpel</hi> under the Apoſtles <hi>Anathema;</hi> and yet <hi>It is not another,</hi> but the clear, pure ſtreams of Goſpel-Truth and Grace are hereby troubled; and the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and comfort of Believers diſturb'd, and the Invitingneſs of it to ſtrangers much obſcur'd and defiled: Now here in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility of the Enemies of the pure Doctrine of the Goſpel is ſeen; That they being afraid to take up the Inſolent, Anti-chriſtian Word; <hi>Merit,</hi> or as the Apoſtle calls it, <hi>Debt.</hi> They would yet Privily bring in ſuch a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed preſence of works after Grace, as <hi>ſincere obedience,</hi> though not <hi>perfect</hi> into Juſtification, as the condition of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37874:46"/> upon which it juſtifies; even as perfect obedience was the condition of the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works;</hi> and yet merit not once Named nor Allowed; Becauſe <hi>Adams</hi> ſtrength to work by, if he had rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed it, was indeed from the Bounty and Goodneſs of the Creator; yet as in a way of Condecency, of ſuch a Creator to ſuch a Creation, as the <hi>Humane Nature;</hi> that came pure and perfect out of His Hand: But what Believers do is from Grace in Chriſt, by and from <hi>His Spirit,</hi> Vouchſafed to Sinners, and ſo cannot <hi>Merit:</hi> Now this hath indeed very great Truth in it; Yet it doth not Anſwer the High Expreſſion of the Goſpel, excluding all Created, or Creature-Righteouſneſs in the Court of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or Juſtification; and placing all in the Righteouſneſs of God by Faith in Jeſus Chriſt; In his obedience, in his Expiation, Filling up, and ſo repleniſhing that Court; That nothing elſe can enter, but is kept out by the <hi>Flaming Sword</hi> of the <hi>Fiery Law:</hi> Yea, Angels that never ſinn'd, yet <hi>Cover their Faces,</hi> Eſa. 6. and their <hi>Feet,</hi> their Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and the <hi>Nakedneſs,</hi> and <hi>Folly</hi> of all Created Being before Increated and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt</hi> in and by Chriſt: Chriſt, as the Head of Amity, and Perſeverance in their Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous State; and <hi>Adam,</hi> not Flying to it upon thoſe tenders of it ſignifid to Him, as by that real evidence of it; That he was, and could be no more, then the <hi>Figure</hi> of Him
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37874:46"/> 
               <hi>that was to come,</hi> Rom. 5. 12. And that His, and His Poſteritys ſtanding in Him, was only their ſtanding in Chriſt; as this was alſo repreſented in thoſe <hi>Sacramental Types, the Tree of the Knowledge of Good and Evil,</hi> Gen. 2. Warning Him againſt ſubſiſting in Himſelf, as a <hi>God knowing,</hi> or able to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil,</hi> but to look to the <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> ſo great a <hi>Type</hi> of Chriſt; as we find in the <hi>Revelation;</hi> Nothing therefore can enter into the Court of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> but Poor empty ſingle Faith Receiving, Owning, Acknowledging, <hi>Grace; Receiving Grace in Abundance,</hi> (excluding all elſe,) and the Gift of Righteouſneſs by Jeſus Chriſt alone; And to this it is enabled by Grace, and Accepted only for that Righteouſneſs ſake it does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</p>
            <p>As to the enforcement by way of Action, and Practice, we ſee in this Great Portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, the Apoſtle gives of a Man in Chriſt; that <hi>Fights the Good Fight, Finiſhes his Courſe, keeps the Faith;</hi> That a Believer in Chriſt is not a Looſe, or an Idle, Slothful, Unactive Perſon; but ſhall appear in <hi>that Day,</hi> as of the <hi>Overcomers</hi> in thoſe ſo Famed Games, or Exerciſes of all Proweſs, Courage, Action; ſo as to be judg'd worthy of <hi>thoſe Crowns</hi> of which they were ſo Ambitious, though but corruptible, by the juſteſt Judges, or Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of them; So the Saints ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented before the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>Eternal Spirit of Holineſs</hi> and before <hi>Saints,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:37874:47"/> and <hi>Angels,</hi> to the Terror, and Amazement of all the Loſt, as Perſons of diſtinct Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency; and the <hi>Overcomers,</hi> as in the <hi>Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyptic</hi> Expreſſion is repeated; and yet all in Chriſt, and to the <hi>Glory,</hi> and <hi>Praiſe of Grace</hi> in Him; So that the Doctrine of Free Grace is indeed the moſt Powerful, Effective, Fruitful Doctrine of Holyneſs, and ſo is moſt Diſcriminative of Perſons in Chriſt, and with greateſt ſeverity on thoſe, who are not; and of thoſe, who ſhall be thought worthy of the <hi>Crown,</hi> and who not; and yet without the leaſt Injury to <hi>Free Grace</hi> in Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Great Conſolation have they, who knew our Deceaſed Friend; who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Admiring, Adoring thoughts of <hi>Free Grace;</hi> and thereby a great ſenſe of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting Holineſs in the Fear of God,</hi> but all through <hi>Chriſt ſtrengthning</hi> Her; and in <hi>Fighting, Running, holding faſt,</hi> an Eye to the Crown, but as purchaſed for her by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; and that therefore ſhe <hi>Loved the Appearance of Jeſus;</hi> When the Crown al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready received, ſhall with Glory be ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her at <hi>that Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we may yet enter into the deeper enquiry into, and conſideration of all this Triumphant Declaration of the Apoſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Himſelf, and all Saints in that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Point; their receiving the <hi>Crown of Righteouſneſs;</hi> I will propoſe to give a breif reſolution of theſe following Points.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:37874:47"/>1. How in the loſt undone State of the Children of <hi>Adam,</hi> there can ariſe ſuch a Generation of Servants of God, both more eminent and ſmaller in this World.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How, or why they fall all under the <hi>Prohibition</hi> of <hi>ſerving God</hi> any longer here in the World, then the <hi>Finiſhing</hi> ſuch a <hi>Courſe</hi> of ſervice on ſuch a <hi>Meaſure</hi> of their <hi>Line</hi> Preſcribed by God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Why this <hi>Prohibition</hi> is ſerv'd upon them by <hi>Death;</hi> Two Perſons only, <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> and why they only excepted.</p>
            <p>Herein I ſhall with all the care and Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on according to the underſtanding given to me by, and from the Word of God Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe each of theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Point.</hi> 1. It is indeed the wonder of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace, and Power; That there ſhould have been, and are ſuch a Generation of the Servants of God in the World, in every Age down to the preſent Time, in the midſt of ſuch a World of Men, Ignorant of God, <hi>Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enated from his Life, without God in the World, without Chriſt and Enemies in their Minds;</hi> ſo much given up to the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Luſts</hi> of it, as to be called; <hi>The World</hi> and the <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>this World,</hi> in a State of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to God, and his Kingdom; the <hi>Seed of the Serpent, the Dragon,</hi> Haters of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and on all opportunities <hi>Slaying them;</hi> as <hi>Cain,</hi> the <hi>Seed</hi> of the <hi>Wicked one,</hi> Did <hi>Abel</hi> in the very Beginning; That yet in the midſt of all theſe, there ſhould be a Generation of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37874:48"/> Men and Women, that ſhould be in an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a courſe, a Lincal ſucceſſion of the Saints and Servants of God, like the ſucceſſion, as in the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Levi,</hi> of the <hi>Preiſthood;</hi> and of the <hi>High Preiſthood</hi> in the Family of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron;</hi> the more Eminent, and the leſs Eminent among the Servants of God; but all a <hi>Royal Prieſthood;</hi> or like the Stars of the <hi>Firſt Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de</hi> in the Regions above, and thoſe they call, the <hi>Sporades,</hi> the Multitude of the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Stars.</p>
            <p>Now the very Root, and Foundation and Corner Stone of all this is; That Grand <hi>Elect Servant</hi> of God, in whom <hi>His Soul delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;</hi> who in Raiſing up a Generation of the Servants of God, dealeth with all mildneſs, <hi>A Bruiſed Reed ſhall He not break, nor ſmok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Flax ſhall He quench,</hi> but ſhall <hi>ſend forth Judgment unto Truth of Victory,</hi> Eſa. 42. 1. That <hi>Servant</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> with the <hi>Key of David on his ſhoulder,</hi> and ſtrengthn'd with the <hi>Girdle</hi> of <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> The <hi>Nail ſaſten'd in a ſure place,</hi> Eſa. 22. 20, &amp;c. Upon whom is <hi>Hung all the Glory of his Fathers Houſe, the off-ſpring,</hi> and the <hi>Iſſue; All Veſſels</hi> of <hi>Greater</hi> and <hi>ſmaller Quantity,</hi> from the <hi>Veſſels of Cups, even to All the Veſſels of Flagons;</hi> Had not He been a Servant in the Foundation, There had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been a <hi>Servant of God in the World.</hi> It is He, who hath <hi>Loved,</hi> and <hi>waſhed in His Blood;</hi> and conſtituted <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Preiſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God</hi> and <hi>His Father,</hi> Rev. 1. 5.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:37874:48"/>
            <p>Now the Charter of His making Servants to God among the Children of Men, was given to the <hi>Second Adam:</hi> Immediately up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Fall of the Firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo quick and immediate as to ſurprize the Power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than in the Firſt Effort; when God in a Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciary proceſs upon Sathan, ſays, to Him, under the diſguiſe of the <hi>Serpent; I will put enmity between thy Seed</hi> and of the <hi>Woman;</hi> and <hi>this Seed of the Woman, the one Seed,</hi> Chriſt ſhall <hi>break the Head</hi> of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> Gen. 3. unto perfect <hi>Victory;</hi> and <hi>Thou ſhall bruiſe His Heel;</hi> (of which is preſently to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken;) There muſt be therefore a Seed of the <hi>Second Adam;</hi> Servants of God in every Generation, who ſhall <hi>Fight, Finiſh their courſe,</hi> Hold <hi>the Faith</hi> of the <hi>Seed</hi> of the <hi>Woman,</hi> the <hi>Second Adam,</hi> the <hi>Lord from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> the <hi>Quickning Spirit, the Saviour to the uttermoſt, who Lives for ever to make Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion,</hi> and ſo ſuſtains all the Servants of God, <hi>coming to God by Him;</hi> He Bears them up in their State of <hi>Preiſthood,</hi> as the <hi>Preiſt for ever; Conſtituted after the Power of an Endleſs Life,</hi> conſecrated by the <hi>word of the Oath for evermore; the High Preiſt and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of our Profeſſion,</hi> the <hi>Captain of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> This ſupports the whole State of the Servants of God in all the Service here recounted here by the Apoſtle; <hi>Fighting, Running, Finiſhing their courſe</hi> in order to the <hi>Receiving the Crown:</hi> And thus the Line of the ſucceſſion of the Servants of God hath
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37874:49"/> been continued from <hi>Adam</hi> through all Ages. From <hi>Adam</hi> by the <hi>Patriarks,</hi> to <hi>Moſes, Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuah,</hi> the <hi>Judges, Kings, Prophets, Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel,</hi> and <hi>Ezra,</hi> ſo to the Great <hi>Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in his Temple,</hi> Malach. 3. 1. Then the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and ſucceſſive <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> Revel. 11. 3. in the Time of the <hi>Apoſtacy;</hi> who being the Laſt courſe of the Servants of God; There is an expreſs mention of that Firſt Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of things; <hi>the Serpent</hi> early appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as a <hi>Dragon</hi> in the <hi>Slaying Abel;</hi> and the <hi>Seed of the Woman,</hi> He endeavoured to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by making War with them,</hi> by the <hi>Beaſt. Who kills them,</hi> and <hi>they Lye Dead in the ſtreet of the Great City;</hi> Till the <hi>Spirit of Life from God enter into them;</hi> And then the courſe of things goes on to the <hi>Binding</hi> the <hi>Dragon, Sathan, the Old Serpent, Chain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Sealing</hi> up in the <hi>Abyſs,</hi> in his own <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Chains</hi> of <hi>Darkneſs;</hi> and then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſhort Looſing to ſhew his ever remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Diabolick</hi> Spirit, we have with all his <hi>Dead</hi> His Final <hi>Caſting</hi> into the <hi>Lake,</hi> which is the <hi>Second Death:</hi> And thus we have the Firſt Point cleared, How comes there to be ſuch a Line and Succeſſion of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> or <hi>Servants</hi> of the <hi>Moſt High God</hi> in ſo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate a Humane Nature? And how Long? Even till they come into the Glorious State of being <hi>Preiſts</hi> of God and Chriſt, and <hi>Reigning with Him a Thouſand Years; ſeeing His Face, as His Servants ſerving Him</hi> with
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37874:49"/> His <hi>Name on their Foreheads,</hi> and at Laſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd up with the <hi>Kingdom to God All in All;</hi> which is the State of pure, and perfect Eternity, <hi>Eternal Life</hi> in its Higheſt Orb.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Point.</hi> 2. I come therefore now to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Point; How comes it to paſs, there is ſuch a ſtrict Limitation of the Servants of God: Firſt under ſuch an Honourable Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as <hi>Fighting</hi> the Good <hi>Fight,</hi> even unto Victory; their <hi>Finiſhing</hi> their <hi>courſe,</hi> even unto <hi>obtaining</hi> the <hi>Prize;</hi> and their <hi>Keeping the Faith,</hi> without betraying, <hi>Baſely</hi> ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, or having <hi>made Shipwrack</hi> of it; and ſo preſenting it before the <hi>Righteous Judge,</hi> and receiving the <hi>Crown at that Day;</hi> All theſe are Honourable, and yet Limitations; Their <hi>Fight, Courſe, Keeping the Faith</hi> are not Leng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then'd out to that very Day; Now of this there are very Great Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Great Lord of Time hath drawn the whole time with ſuch exactneſs of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Holineſs; That every thing is in its own Place, Seaſon, and Time; and as it fills that up, and nothing is wanting, ſo it cannot exceed, nor reach beyond it; And thus <hi>Every thing is Beautiful in its ſeaſon;</hi> Thus from the very Beginning; <hi>Abel</hi> the Firſt Martyr <hi>Finiſhed</hi> his <hi>Courſe,</hi> though ſhort; <hi>Enoch, Noah, Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> theirs; In the midſt of whom appeared <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec, made like to the Son of God, without Beginning of Days,</hi> or End of Life, Abridgeth a <hi>Preiſt continually;</hi> He was not a Type of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37874:50"/> 
               <hi>Son of God</hi> in ſome particular excellency, but <hi>He was made like to the Son of God throughout;</hi> And thus is the Line of every Saints ſervice drawn out, nothing can crowd into it; and this Line can by no Violence be cut ſhorter, nor can any Zeal for Service draw it out longer; The only Elect Servant is He, whoſe Service hath no Limitation; but, as was ſaid, <hi>The Son Conſecrated by the Word of the Oath for evermore; and conſtituted after the Power of an Endleſs Life: Melchiſedec</hi> therefore, who was made like Him, was under no Limitation of Service in the Hiſtory we have of Him: <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs Patriarchal</hi> Line reach'd even to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and there ceaſed; <hi>Moſes Faithful in All his Houſe</hi> Run that whole, and very Great Line of Service in the <hi>Wilderneſs;</hi> but was ſo Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, He muſt by no means enter into <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> but muſt Dye in the Borders; And <hi>Joſhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> muſt enter upon his Courſe; and having ſettled the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Canaan,</hi> and after the <hi>Lord had given them reſt round about; He Finiſhed his courſe.</hi> Then came on the <hi>Days</hi> of the <hi>Judges,</hi> and their courſe with <hi>Samuel</hi> reached (with the Intervention of <hi>Saul)</hi> unto <hi>David,</hi> who <hi>ſerved his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration according to the Will of God;</hi> And ſo the Line came down to <hi>John Baptiſt Fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling</hi> his <hi>courſe,</hi> as a <hi>Forerunner;</hi> and ſo to our <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> who <hi>walked,</hi> as He ſaid in his courſe here on Earth, (though as the <hi>Son, an Eternal Prieſt) this Day,</hi> and to <hi>Morrow;</hi> and the <hi>Third Day</hi> ſhould be <hi>perfected.</hi> Then
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37874:50"/> the courſe of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> under a moſt Definitive Line, as hath been ſaid: This therefore gives great ſatisfaction in the Term of Life; Calls for Great ſelf-Reſignation, and to have our Eye Fixed on the Great End of Life, the Line of Faith and Service.</p>
            <p>It is true, There is a Line allowed to Evil Men in their Wickedneſs, and in their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments of their Luſts, and Pleaſures of this World; and they cannot exceed it; But this is not of the preſent conſideration; But it is moſt neceſſary here to remember; That the Loweſt and Meaneſt, even the Infant Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God have their Line and Service, and the Juſt Times of it Fixed by God; even as their Reward; becauſe it is wholly the Reward of Free Grace, It is in the eſſence of the Reward equal, as hath been argued.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Time of the Servants of God is therefore Defined, and Limited; That it may be ſeen, God hath no need of this, or that Servant, or Generation of Servants; but that He hath ſucceſſive Servants, or Generations of Servants; and He is ſo Far off being in want of them; That He can allow them no longer Time, how Eminent, how Excellent ſoever, then He hath appointed, and reſolved with Himſelf; and of Free Grace, as their Honour and Priviledge, choſen them unto.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Servants of God are <hi>many;</hi> That they may reach through, and unto the Time of his <hi>Kingdom;</hi> And each muſt have His
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37874:51"/> Time; and each muſt therefore, of thoſe, who go before, give way to thoſe, who are to follow after; and ſo every one is Limited to his own Time; For though it may be thought; They might be together; The Wiſe God having appointed Times more Dark, and more Glorious; How many of his Servants are proportion'd to each, He ſees, and knows, and ſo Limits accordingly: There was one <hi>Noah,</hi> and no more in the Old World; One <hi>Elijah</hi> only in view, in that ſo Fowl <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> of the <hi>Ten Tribes;</hi> And when the Light is cleareſt and moſt High, It muſt not be clear Light till his Kingdom. The General Aſſembly cannot be before, ſo each Time hath ſuch, and ſuch <hi>Numbers</hi> of <hi>Stars,</hi> which He <hi>telleth the Number</hi> of, and <hi>calleth them All by their Names,</hi> and knoweth, what Luſtre of Rays and Beams each and together ſhall caſt; There is a Counterpoizing conſideration of Wicked Men in the World, and the <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and <hi>Fire</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> they ſpread; But that is not within the preſent purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There is a Gracious Pleaſure of God; There ſhould ſuch Numbers of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants be all along from Age to Age with <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt their Lord,</hi> Philip. 1. <hi>Diſſolved</hi> from Body, and with Him in Spirit; <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the Body,</hi> and <hi>preſent with the Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in their <hi>Houſe not made</hi> with <hi>Hands, Eternal in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens;</hi> And that <hi>our God may come</hi> and <hi>All</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:37874:51"/> 
               <hi>His Saints with Him,</hi> Zech. 14. <hi>He cometh with Ten Thouſand of his Saints,</hi> as the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Heaven on white Horſes, Bodys of the Reſurrection waſhed in the Blood of Jeſus, in fine Linnen, clean, and white,</hi> Rev. 19. 14. To ſhew, This hath been all along from the former Times of the World; There is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception in Heaven Styled, <hi>Abrahams Boſome; A Jeruſalem above, the Mother of us All,</hi> that ſhall <hi>come down from Heaven,</hi> Gal. 4. With all its <hi>Children,</hi> Rev. 21. There is the State of the <hi>Spirits of Juſt Men,</hi> Heb. 12. Who ſhall be <hi>made perfect in Bodys, made like to his Glorious Body,</hi> Phil. 3. <hi>ult.</hi> There muſt be therefore a Limitation of their Time of Service here below; That they may be taken within the <hi>Veil</hi> and made acquainted with the Glory, that is to be <hi>Revealed;</hi> And the Apoſtle Intimates; Theſe <hi>Dead in Chriſt</hi> ſhall have ſome precedency; For the <hi>Dead in Chriſt,</hi> ſhall not be <hi>prevented</hi> by the <hi>Living Remaining,</hi> as we Tranſlate; but ſhall not be ſo much, as overtaken according to the true force of the Original; we ſhall not <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> or <hi>come equal</hi> with thoſe aſleep, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> c. 4. v. 13. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Nullo Modo Aſſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur;</hi> Now in all ſuch Particularities, God is pleas'd to be at Liberty in dealing with His own Servants; The eſſential Glory, the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> the <hi>Crown of Life,</hi> the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Glory</hi> being alike, ſure to all: And ſo I have open'd the ſecond Point pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd; The Limitation of the Time of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37874:52"/> Servants of God, <hi>continuing</hi> in His <hi>Service</hi> here on Earth; I come to the <hi>Point</hi> 3d.</p>
            <p>3. That the Limitation of their Time is made known to them in the manner of a ſevere, and angry Proceſs, in the way of, what we Call, a <hi>Prohibition,</hi> the proper ſenſe of what we Tranſlate, <hi>not ſaffered,</hi> Heb. 7. 23. And this is a Point worthy to be enquired into for the removing the fears of Death, and for the Conſolation of Saints in Death</p>
            <p n="1">1. It muſt then be Acknowledg'd, that the outward Face, and appearance of Death, bears the Reſemblance of a <hi>Judgment,</hi> and of that Denunciation, <hi>In the Day thou Eateſt, thou ſhalt Dye; Duſt thou Art,</hi> and to <hi>Duſt thou ſhalt return.</hi> It comes, as a <hi>King of Terrors, Fleſh and Blood</hi> is ready to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted at it; Life is naturally Dear, even to the Servants of God; who deſire not to be <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloathed;</hi> They deſire to continue in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God here; but when they are raiſed by Higher Conſiderations of being <hi>preſent with the Lord, Clothed upon with their Houſe from Heaven,</hi> they even deſire to be <hi>Diſſolved.</hi> And it cannot be denyed; That God doth in the Dying of his Servants bear a Regard to that Juſtice, and Truth of His Word; That when <hi>Sin came in, Death came in and paſſed upon All, becauſe All have ſinned,</hi> Rom. 5. 12. Wheu the Servants of God therefore are warm and zealous, and lively in His Service, Often there comes a <hi>Prohibition;</hi> Thou mayeſt no longer continue in my Service
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37874:52"/> here; like the command to <hi>Moſes,</hi> to anoint <hi>Eleazar</hi> and to ſtrip <hi>Aaron</hi> of his Prieſtly Garments, who was preſently to Dye; A <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> to <hi>carry Iſrael</hi> over <hi>Jordan,</hi> but to come up to <hi>Mount Nebo</hi> and to Dye; <hi>Deut.</hi> 33. God plainly ſent to <hi>Hezekiah, to ſet His Houſe in Order</hi> and to <hi>Dye;</hi> againſt which <hi>Prohibition</hi> that it might be under, as it were an Arreſt of Judgment, He ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly Prayed.</p>
            <p>It is therefore to be duly conſidered; That for the Diſplay of the Judgment, and Indignation of God againſt ſin, and becauſe of the preſent State of the Saints under a Remaining <hi>Body of Sin,</hi> and ſo of <hi>Death;</hi> and in the preſent State of this World, full of Sin and Evil, and of ſo many of the Children of <hi>Adam, Children of Death,</hi> even of the <hi>Second Death;</hi> In the Wiſdom and Holineſs of God, It was by the Counſel of the Father, and the Son, that <hi>Death</hi> ſhould continue, and have the Face of a Judgment, and of a <hi>Legal Prohibition</hi> to continue in the Service of God any longer on Earth; Till the Kingdom of Chriſt, the Kingdom of Redemption ſhould bring in a State of the <hi>Living</hi> Saints, then <hi>Remaining</hi> being <hi>chang'd,</hi> and not to <hi>Dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Becauſe the Children</hi> were <hi>Partakers</hi> of <hi>Fleſh and Blood,</hi> He <hi>took part of the ſame,</hi> that <hi>through Death,</hi> He <hi>might ſubdue Him, that had the Power of Death;</hi> that is, the <hi>Devil;</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:37874:53"/> and <hi>Deliver</hi> them, who <hi>all their Life were ſubject to Bondage by reaſon of the Fear of Death;</hi> and now therefore Death came upon Him with the Violence, and Terror of a <hi>Judgment</hi> from which He was taken and from <hi>Priſon,</hi> Eſa. 53. 8. By the Mighty Power of his Reſurrection; It becomes all His to ſubmit then to the Face of a Judgment in Dying, that they may be conform'd to their <hi>Captain</hi> and from the Firſt Born, Heb. 2. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> It may be Objected againſt this neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Dying, How were thoſe two <hi>Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> exempted from that ſentence of the Righteous, and Holy Law that is ſtretched out ſo upon all; ſeeing ſin had extended it ſelf on them, as well, as on others?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Death of Jeſus Chriſt, ſtood as a <hi>Full Ranſom,</hi> and Price of Redemption from the very firſt promiſe, ſo that it is not indeed a Point of Juſtice, or of the Truth of God; That Believers in Jeſus Chriſt are ſerved (as I may ſo ſpeak) with a <hi>Prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> by <hi>Death;</hi> but a Wiſe, and Holy Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of Government with Relation to the Servants of God in the preſent World; where therefore, in that wiſe Government God thinks fit; there might be ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption from the General Statute of Dying, or <hi>Prohibition</hi> by <hi>Death,</hi> as of <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elijah;</hi> and many more Examples of ſuch Exemptions, there might have been, if He had ſeen Good, having received ſuch full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to his Law, and to his Juſtice;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37874:53"/> and He hath it in reſerve an Univerſal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption at the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of <hi>Redemption;</hi> when the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>We ſhall not all dye,</hi> but <hi>we ſhall all be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged;</hi> and he prefaces before it: <hi>Behold I ſhew you a myſtery;</hi> And I am much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded and even aſſured; Theſe two were Types of the <hi>Living, Remaining caught up</hi> to <hi>meet</hi> the <hi>Lord in the Air,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. <hi>He delivers up the Kingdom</hi> to <hi>God, even the Father,</hi> and hath <hi>put down all Rule Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> and the <hi>laſt Enemy</hi> and <hi>caſt it into the Lake,</hi> Rev. 20. <hi>ult.</hi> When the Gentle Hand of Power ſhall Tranſpoſe the Saints; as the Great <hi>Prophet Enoch,</hi> of the Lord coming with <hi>Ten Thouſand</hi> of his Saints, and the <hi>Living Remaining changed,</hi> and the <hi>Flames of Fire</hi> upon <hi>All Enemies,</hi> ſhall convey them as in <hi>Elijahs Chariot</hi> to Heaven.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Judiciary part of Death is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely removed; <hi>For the Sting of Death is Sin,</hi> and the <hi>ſtrength of Sin is the Law, but thanks be to God</hi> who hath <hi>given us the Victory</hi> through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 12. So that Death is to Saints, a <hi>ſleeping in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, a Reſting from Labours, an entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Reſt, a becoming preſent with the Lord; A being with Chriſt, a being in Paradiſe, a being clothed upon with our Houſe from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> And to ſhew, It was not a Deadly ſtroke; Before the Pronunciation of that Univerſal <hi>Prohibition</hi> of continuing here;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37874:54"/> 
               <hi>Duſt thou Art, and to Duſt thou ſhalt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn;</hi> Death was more gently expreſs'd, and with aſſurance of <hi>Victory; The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Seed ſhall break the Serpents, Head,</hi> but the <hi>Serpent</hi> ſhall only <hi>Bruiſe the Heel of the Womans Seed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Applic.</hi> I will now by way of Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Review, cloſe the whole; How fit this Context of the Apoſtle is to a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with Relation to the Death of one, or more of the Servants of God, appears by the Apoſtles Preface to it; I am even now as it were already, as in Conformity to my Great Lord Offered, and Sacrificed, as a <hi>Martyr,</hi> and the <hi>Time</hi> of my <hi>Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is at <hi>Hand;</hi> and ſo He goes on, <hi>I have Fought,</hi> &amp;c. As if He Preached his own <hi>Funeral Sermon,</hi> while Living, and a Great one it is; but it hath its Principal ſenſe in Chriſt; and in God; as appears in the following Part of the Chapter, <hi>v.</hi> 17. wherein we have this Great acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, that in his <hi>Fighting the Good Fight, and Finiſhing his Courſe, the Lord ſtood with Him, ſtrengthened Him; that by Him the Preaching might be Fully known, and the Gentiles hear, and the Lord De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered Him, out of the Mouth of the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Lord would deliver Him from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Evil Work, and preſerve Him unto His Heavenly Kingdom, and to Him he aſcribes the Glory of All for Ever;</hi> And He In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37874:54"/> all Saints; Even all, who <hi>Love the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> this High <hi>Elogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> or Speech of Praiſe, elſe I muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, I have no Opinion of the Large <hi>Encomiums,</hi> or Praiſings uſed in Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Sermons, obſerving the Grand Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar of them; Gods Gracious Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of <hi>Moſes,</hi> John 1. <hi>Moſes my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant is Dead</hi> and no more, and yet that Fixed ſo Daſhing a Character of Honour upon Him; that He is remembred by it to the Laſt, Rev. 15. <hi>They Sang the Song of Moſes the Servant of God, and of the Lamb:</hi> But this of the Apoſtle Joyned with that of <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 23. Gives me ſuch a Hiſtory of the Life and Death of Saints; That I cannot, but Recommend it to all the Servants of Chriſt, as the moſt excellent Rule of Life, and as the Ground of the moſt Conſolatory <hi>Hope in Death,</hi> and that the very Diſcourſe of it may be upon the Deceaſed Chriſtian Friend a Memorial of Honour; And ſo I moſt Humbly Recommend it to the Relations of all the Friends of the ſo many lately Removed Servants of God, and of this Particular one, the occaſion of whoſe Death it is Publiſhed; through Him, who though the <hi>Eternal Liver,</hi> as the <hi>Son of God</hi> without <hi>Beginning,</hi> or <hi>End</hi> of <hi>Days,</hi> yet in our Nature <hi>Became Dead</hi> for our ſakes, but behold He is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37874:55"/> 
               <hi>Alive for Evermore;</hi> Even ſo have all his Servants Reaſon to ſay, <hi>Even ſo Amen.</hi> And He hath the. <hi>Keys of Hell,</hi> and <hi>Death;</hi> Let Him <hi>Lay His Hand</hi> on his <hi>Servants of God</hi> in this Diſcourſe, and Bleſs it to Them and to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of all States and Conditions; ſaying unto them, <hi>Fear not. And to Him be Glory for Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37874:55"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
